<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tvvo famous pitcht battels of Lypsich, and Lutzen wherein the ever-renowned Prince Gustavus the Great lived and died a conquerour: with an elegie upon his untimely death, composed in heroick verse by John Russell, Master of Arts, of Magdalene Coll. in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Russell, John, d. 1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11194</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116282</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851499</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851499</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16773</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11194)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16773)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 974:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tvvo famous pitcht battels of Lypsich, and Lutzen wherein the ever-renowned Prince Gustavus the Great lived and died a conquerour: with an elegie upon his untimely death, composed in heroick verse by John Russell, Master of Arts, of Magdalene Coll. in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Russell, John, d. 1688.</author>
                  <author>Russell, John, d. 1688. Elegie upon the death of the most illustrious and victorious Prince Gustavus Adolphus King of Swethland &amp;c. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by [Thomas and John Buck] the printers to the Vniversitie of Cambridge. 1634. And are to be sold by Philip Scarlet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1634]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>"An elegie upon the immature and much lamented death of that most Christian souldier and renowned prince, Gustavus the Great", a reprint of Russell's "An elegie upon the death of the most illustrious and victorious Prince Gustavus Adolphus King of Swethland &amp;c.", has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>A variant (STC 21460.3) lacks "And are to be sold by Philip Scarlet" in imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gustaf --  II Adolf, --  King of Sweden, 1594-1632 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Leipzig, Battle of, 1631 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lützen, Battle of, 1632 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="illustration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:1"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>
                           <hi>GUSTAVE ADOLPHE</hi> Roy de Suede Tué à la Bataille de Lutz ente 16. g.<hi rend="sup">bre</hi> 1632 agé de 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ans.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:1"/>
                  <p>THE Tvvo Famous Pitcht Battels of LYPSICH, AND LUTZEN; Wherein the ever-renowned Prince GUSTAVUS THE GREAT lived and died a Conquerour: WITH AN ELEGIE UPON his untimely death, compoſed in Heroick Verſe By JOHN RUSSELL, <hi>Maſter of Arts, of</hi> Magdalene <hi>Coll. in</hi> CAMBRIDGE.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—<hi>Me</hi> caſtra juvant, &amp; lituo tubae</l>
                     <l>Permiſtus ſonitus, belláque matribus</l>
                     <l>Deteſtata —</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Printed by the Printers to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie</hi> of CAMBRIDGE. 1634.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And are to be ſold by</hi> Philip Scarlet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:2"/>
                  <head>AD NOBILISSIMVM SUUM PATRONUM <hi>EPIGRAMMA.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> mihi ſis <hi>Phoebus,</hi> mea ſit tibi <hi>Luna</hi> libellus,</l>
                  <l>Quem facis (en!) radiis ipſe micare tuis.</l>
                  <l>Sidereos volui titulos, &amp; nomina clara</l>
                  <l>Supremâ in noſtri figere parte libri,</l>
                  <l>Quò poſſent plenè ſuffundere luce coruſcâ</l>
                  <l>Quaelibet in ſcriptis inferiora meis.</l>
                  <l>Jam mea ſi <hi>Livor</hi> contorto lumine ſpectet</l>
                  <l>Carmina, <hi>percuſſus ſydere,</hi> mutus erit.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, TRUELY VALOUROUS, AND HEROICK GENTLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, WILLIAM Lord CRAVEN, BARON of <hi>Hampſteed,</hi> MARSHALL, &amp;c.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RABLE,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ardent affection wherewith the beſt &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limeſt Spirits have ever embraced the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of the <hi>Muſes,</hi> is not in any example ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, as in that matchleſſe pattern of true <hi>Valour</hi> and <hi>Magnificence, ALEXANDER</hi> the Great; who having finiſht the Conqueſt of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and hearing every day of more Victories, did thus expreſſe his ſorrow and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented affection; <hi>Think you to pleaſe me with any news, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ye can tell me that HOMER is alive again?</hi> Such was his ambitious love to <hi>Poetrie.</hi> Under protection of this invincible example, I boldly make my <hi>Approaches.</hi> My <hi>Lines</hi> are alreadie drawn and perfected, whereby I am reſolved to attempt your Lordſhips Favour; and I hope I ſhall winne the ſame without any danger or repulſe. Yet do I not think to carrie it by any advantageous ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, or forcible irruption; but onely by a free and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie yeelding, which you may eaſily perform, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any derogation to your <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Valour.</hi> And ſeeing now my ſpeech is to a <hi>Souldier,</hi> give me leave in that little that I have to ſpeak, to keep the ſame dialect. Foraſmuch as I am now to expoſe my ſelf to a World
<pb facs="tcp:16773:3"/>
of Enemies, I thought it fit to marſhall theſe my lines after a warlike order. I have prefixed the approbations of my judicious in the front of this Book, to be as it were a <hi>Vantguard.</hi> Then followes in the middle my own Poem, which I account as the <hi>Main;</hi> and upon this I do moſt of all relie. Then I have reſerved in the laſt place ſome few <hi>Elegiack</hi> Verſes; which becauſe they have alreadie paſt the <hi>Pikes</hi> of ſharpeſt cenſures, and come off cleare in the judgement of the world, I make them my laſt refuge, and have placed them (as you may ſee) in the <hi>Rear.</hi> In this order I ſtand readie to receive the aſſaults of envious <hi>Carpers,</hi> and curious <hi>Criticks.</hi> I do not ſtand in any fear of your Honourable acceptation, and gracious interpretation of theſe my labours. The name and ſubject of my Book, which is <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> Battels, is enough to aſſure me from all doubts &amp; ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions. Seeing you have not thought much to ſpend your beſt bloud in defence of his cauſe, I cannot think you will be backward to patronize the memorie of his Name.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>The unfeigned Admirer of your Heroick Vertues,</hi> JOHN RUSSELL.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:3"/>
                  <head>To the Candid Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Eſt any <hi>Cynicall Critick</hi> ſhould compare my book to the Town of <hi>Mindas,</hi> which being but a ſmall Citie, was notwithſtanding beautified with ſtately gates; I am in this reſpect forced to Apologize for my ſelf, and my learned <hi>Friends,</hi> who have adorned this ſmall volume of mine with their ample <hi>Approbations.</hi> Know then, Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous <hi>Reader,</hi> that I could not ſubtract theſe <hi>Encomiaſticks,</hi> without apparent wrong to the ſubject of my Book: for you ſhall finde that they have imitated that cunning Engraver, who had with ſuch art inwrought his own <hi>Image</hi> with the <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Minerva,</hi> that they could not be ſeparated without defacing of both: ſo have my <hi>Friends</hi> here interwoven my moſt undeſerving <hi>Name</hi> with the ſublime praiſes of <hi>GU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STAVUS,</hi> that the one cannot be ſeparated from the other, without manifeſt disfiguring of the <hi>Poem.</hi> Beſides, there are ſome that are more delighted with brief &amp; conciſe Epitomes, then with larger Treatiſes: theſe Verſes which I have premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſeem to have contracted that which I have more amply handled, the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Praiſe</hi> of <hi>GUSTAVUS</hi> the <hi>Great.</hi> And to conclude, that which theſe <hi>Criticks</hi> would fain make an argument of arrogance and oſtentation, ſeems to me a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous teſtimonie of my timorouſneſſe and modeſtie, in that I dare not enter into the world, without ſo many to guard me and uſher me the way. Farewell.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. R.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:4"/>
                  <head>TO HIS FRIEND THE AVTHOVR, <hi>IN DEFENCE OF HIS Heroick Poem.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat wilt thou anſwer, <hi>Poet,</hi> for this wrong,</l>
                  <l>To make a <hi>King</hi> thy <hi>Subject</hi> and thy <hi>Song;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>King,</hi> whoſe Fame and long-liv'd actions ſcarce</l>
                  <l>Can be contain'd in meaſure of a verſe?</l>
                  <l>O inconſiderate Muſe! Of him is't fit</l>
                  <l>That every budget brain and common wit</l>
                  <l>Should write a farthing Pamphlet? Every one</l>
                  <l>At's death can have a verſe in braſſe and ſtone.</l>
                  <l>Thus will cenſorious <hi>Criticks</hi> talk, and thoſe</l>
                  <l>That th' Empire claim of <hi>Poetrie</hi> and <hi>Proſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet care not. Once <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> was a ſcoffe,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Tinker</hi> call'd; at laſt came bravely off:</l>
                  <l>He clipt the <hi>Eagles</hi> wings, and took from thence</l>
                  <l>A quill for thee, <hi>Fabritius:</hi> art thou ſince</l>
                  <l>Silent? Go, take thy pen, grave <hi>Doctour,</hi> write:</l>
                  <l>Thy Muſe methinks this Poem might excite.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. PULLEN, <hi>Fellow of</hi> Magd. <hi>Coll.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:5"/>
                  <head>TO HIS FRIEND THE A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R of this Heroick Poem.</head>
                  <l>I Nothing finde unhappie in thy Book,</l>
                  <l>But (what's not thine) the ſubject. When I look</l>
                  <l>Upon thy <hi>Muſe,</hi> and finde it full of bloud,</l>
                  <l>Yet I conclude thy <hi>Vein</hi> is ſound and good,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall live long by that which is not thine,</l>
                  <l>But lively repreſented in thy line.</l>
                  <l>That Hero's death thou doſt with life declare,</l>
                  <l>And in that which thou giv'ſt thou'lt ſurely ſhare.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. BULKLEY, <hi>Fellow of</hi> S. Johns <hi>Coll.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>To my Friend Maſter <hi>RUSSELL,</hi> upon this enſuing Poem of the King of Swedens Battels.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'TWas a Proud <hi>Greek,</hi> whoſe vaſt Ambition</l>
                     <l>Pin'd for new <hi>Worlds,</hi> who vow'd his <hi>Counterfeit</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Should be pourtraid on pain of death by none,</l>
                     <l>But beſt <hi>Apelles.</hi> Pride ſurnam'd him <hi>Great.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And 'twas a prouder <hi>Tuſcan,</hi> miſemployd</l>
                     <l>His dying thoughts about his <hi>Elegie;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Charging his <hi>Marble</hi> might be rather void,</l>
                     <l>Then not adorn'd by Prince of <hi>Poetrie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thus did not <hi>Sweden</hi> taint his greatneſſe: He</l>
                     <l>Suffers all Proſe, or Verſe. Nor doth his <hi>Shade</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Diſturb, but help the <hi>Artiſt.</hi> Deitie</l>
                     <l>Accepts an offring from the meaneſt trade.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16773:5"/>
                        <hi>Friend,</hi> thy firſt-fruits are ſacred. <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAVES</hi> Name</l>
                     <l>Is then (O <hi>Muſes</hi>) more authenticall.</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhall't be <hi>Hereſie</hi> in verſe to claim</l>
                     <l>Aid from live <hi>Names,</hi> and ſtill <hi>Imperiall.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He ſhall preſerve thy <hi>Papers,</hi> and vent more</l>
                     <l>Then an enlarg'd <hi>Edition.</hi> His <hi>Name</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall be thy <hi>Title</hi> too, and fill the doore</l>
                     <l>Of the rich Shop it lies in; like the Frame</l>
                     <l>Of ſome rare <hi>Frontiſpice,</hi> with neat device</l>
                     <l>Tying unto it the Spectatours eyes.</l>
                     <l>So both in equall tye are excellent;</l>
                     <l>Thy Book's His <hi>Elegie,</hi> He its <hi>Monument.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHat looſe <hi>Proſe</hi> could not pay to <hi>Swedens</hi> Herſe,</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt diſcharg'd in thy Heroick Verſe,</l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>Intelligencers</hi> Feet, on which he'l runne</l>
                     <l>Now round the world, like a ſurveying <hi>Sunne.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Twas greater art to chuſe thy Theme, then write</l>
                     <l>Some <hi>Poems.</hi> But to pen it in deſpite</l>
                     <l>Of others grief, or ſilence, argues <hi>Love</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Great as thy <hi>Art.</hi> And if the People prove</l>
                     <l>Thy hand hath rudely op't a publick wound</l>
                     <l>Newly clos'd up; the <hi>Magiſtrate's</hi> not bound</l>
                     <l>(As <hi>Athens</hi> mulcted <hi>Phrenicus</hi>) to be</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Cenſor,</hi> and to fine thy <hi>Hiſtorie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No: Let us know, our Guilt that <hi>Matchleſſe Man,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe <hi>Dirge</hi> thou ſing'ſt, hath murdred. Nay, I can,</l>
                     <l>And dare tell how too: 'Twas the fond exceſſe</l>
                     <l>Of our big thoughts decreas'd his Happineſſe;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe modeſt <hi>Soul</hi> we vext with reſtleſſe crie</l>
                     <l>Of love pretended, Proud <hi>Idolatrie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16773:6"/>His purer <hi>Breaſt</hi> divin'd aſmuch, while we</l>
                     <l>Mad men ſtill tempted him with <hi>Propheſie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oh! had this Frenzie reſted in the heart</l>
                     <l>Onely of us the People, little Art</l>
                     <l>Might frame a Plea. But our great <hi>Rabbins</hi> too,</l>
                     <l>(Oh <hi>Learning,</hi> what huge miſchiefs mayſt thou do,</l>
                     <l>Seduc'd by Pride and Flatt'rie!) nay, thoſe <hi>Brains</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That wear the <hi>Sacred Cappe,</hi> through all their veins</l>
                     <l>Deſcri'd infected bloud, whoſe tainted ſtreams</l>
                     <l>Danger'd the <hi>Nations,</hi> whil'ſt noiſome ſteams</l>
                     <l>Exhal'd as high as Heav'n. That ſtarrie Sphere,</l>
                     <l>Stranger to vapours, could not now be cleare.</l>
                     <l>Egypt examin'd Starres, and father'd lies</l>
                     <l>On their pure Subſtances: all <hi>Myſteries</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are pri'd into, and ſtretcht. The <hi>Chiliaſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Takes ſev'rall ſhapes; now poſes us in vaſt</l>
                     <l>Contemplative juſt nothings, and then ſlips</l>
                     <l>Into a <hi>Caſſock,</hi> picks th' <hi>Apocalyps,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſhowes us Wonders, which poore I dare ſwear</l>
                     <l>His fleering heart well knew were never there.</l>
                     <l>The unclaſpt <hi>Book</hi> was read, the <hi>Signes</hi> unſeal'd,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Trumpets, Phials,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt</hi> reveal'd:</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Ceſar</hi> ſlain outright, and all</l>
                     <l>By <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAVE,</hi> and by <hi>Heav'n.</hi> This was his fall.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sinne</hi> was ours; the troubled <hi>Vertue</hi> his.</l>
                     <l>So <hi>Evil</hi> haſted <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> to her bliſſe.</l>
                     <l>Now th' <hi>An'grams</hi> bluſh: and had not <hi>Pirrhus</hi> art</l>
                     <l>Excus'd the letter, when the <hi>Authours</hi> heart</l>
                     <l>Glow'd with a lie; by this time <hi>Levi</hi> had,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Iſs'chars aſſe,</hi> coucht under's burden, glad,</l>
                     <l>Though ſtrong, to be releas'd. Let this ſuffice,</l>
                     <l>We all confeſſe we ſlew him, and our eyes</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16773:6"/>Shall teſtifie our ſorrows. LYPSICH may,</l>
                     <l>And LUTZEN tell his <hi>Life</hi> ſome half the way:</l>
                     <l>What we confeſſe, tells all; perfects the Storie</l>
                     <l>More then the Annals of his living <hi>Glorie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oh! this Confeſſion well-penn'd would be</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Chronicle,</hi> his <hi>Tombe,</hi> his <hi>Elegie.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>T. RILEY, <hi>Fellow of</hi> Trin. <hi>Coll.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>TO THE A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R OF this enſuing <hi>Poem,</hi> Maſter <hi>RUSSELL.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>HOw dares thy mortall <hi>Fancie</hi> undertake</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Theme Divine,</hi> unleſſe for <hi>Vertues</hi> ſake?</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Germane Eagle,</hi> to advance thy skill</l>
                  <l>In praiſing <hi>Swethland,</hi> lends a conqu'red quill.</l>
                  <l>Yet when thy <hi>Self</hi> and loftie <hi>Bird</hi> have done,</l>
                  <l>Neither are able to behold this <hi>Sunne.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Go ſtrive to write, and caſt away thy pen:</l>
                  <l>Repent thy ſelf, and take it up agen.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes thy ſelf, and ſometimes <hi>Swethland</hi> blame:</l>
                  <l>And midſt thy praiſes check his glorious <hi>Name.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tell valiant <hi>Swethland,</hi> if thy <hi>Eagle</hi> brings</l>
                  <l>A flight too low, his Greatneſſe clipt her wings.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CAESAR WILLIAMSON, <hi>Fellow of</hi> Trinit. <hi>Colledge.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:7"/>
                  <head>To his ingenious <hi>Friend</hi> Maſter <hi>RUSSELL,</hi> upon his Heroick <hi>Poem.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>LEt thoſe ſoft <hi>Poets,</hi> who have dipt their brains</l>
                  <l>In am'rous humours, thaw to looſer ſtrains.</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Cupid</hi> be their theme, and let them pay</l>
                  <l>Service to <hi>Venus</hi> in a wanton lay:</l>
                  <l>And let theſe <hi>Rhymers</hi> of our ſilken Age</l>
                  <l>Unlade their Fancies on an emptie page.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mars</hi> is thy theme; thy <hi>Muſe</hi> hath learn'd to talk</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Cannon-language</hi> of the Warre, and walk</l>
                  <l>A loftie March; while thy faint readers dread</l>
                  <l>And tremble at each ſyllable they reade.</l>
                  <l>Leade on, Stout Poet, in thy Martiall ſtate;</l>
                  <l>And let theſe <hi>Pages</hi> on <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> wait,</l>
                  <l>Armed with verſe of proof: and thoſe that aim</l>
                  <l>To wound thy <hi>Muſe,</hi> or print upon thy Name</l>
                  <l>Their darts of malice, in their full purſuit,</l>
                  <l>Charm'd like thoſe ſtones thrown at the <hi>Thracian Lute,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May they forget their meſſage, and in fierce</l>
                  <l>Career dance at the muſick of thy verſe.</l>
                  <l>And if thoſe eyes, with pois'ned flame that ſhine</l>
                  <l>Like Baſilisks, ſhed poiſon on a line,</l>
                  <l>To blot a ſyllable that ſounds the leaſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> Warre, <hi>Jove</hi> turn them to that Beaſt.</l>
                  <l>Then reſt <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S:</hi> do not change thy room</l>
                  <l>Within this Book, for any marble tombe.</l>
                  <l>Each line's a golden chain to hoiſe thee farre</l>
                  <l>'Bove <hi>Fate:</hi> then blaze as faſtned to a ſtarre:</l>
                  <l>And for theſe <hi>Leaves</hi> preſented thee, a <hi>bough</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Laurell</hi> ſhall adorn the <hi>Poets</hi> brow.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>JOHN SALTMARSH, Magd. <hi>Coll.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:7"/>
                  <head>To his friend the <hi>AUTHOUR.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>INgenious friend, that doſt ſo bravely ſing</l>
                  <l>The conqueſts of the <hi>Swethes</hi> Victorious King;</l>
                  <l>Who by thy thundring lines doſt ſeem to follow</l>
                  <l>Aſwell the tents of <hi>Mars,</hi> as of <hi>Apollo;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in depainting of a bloudie fight</l>
                  <l>Doſt intermingle <hi>Terrour</hi> with <hi>Delight:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though I could tell thee that thy verſes worth</l>
                  <l>Abundantly will gild and ſet them forth;</l>
                  <l>Although I might (without baſe flatterie) ſay</l>
                  <l>Thy forehead doth deſerve a wreathe or Bay;</l>
                  <l>Yet I forbear: thy modeſtie is ſuch,</l>
                  <l>I dare not praiſe, at leaſt, not praiſe thee much.</l>
                  <l>Indeed what need'ſt thou my too ſlender praiſe,</l>
                  <l>To uſher thy ſo ſweetly-ſoaring layes</l>
                  <l>Into the world; ſince that the very name</l>
                  <l>GUSTAVUS will more highly grace the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Then if the rareſt <hi>Laureats</hi> choiſeſt quill</l>
                  <l>To pen thy praiſe ſhould ſhew its utmoſt skill?</l>
                  <l>How richly is thy work rewarded! See!</l>
                  <l>Thou mak'ſt GUSTAVUS live, GUSTAVUS thee:</l>
                  <l>And by thy loftie Muſe I know not now</l>
                  <l>Whether ſhall more be honour'd, he or thou.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sweds</hi> Great<note n="*" place="margin">Anagram of <hi>GUSTAVUS</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S!</hi> Oh how could I dwell</l>
                  <l>Upon that Name! How often could I ſpell</l>
                  <l>Its every ſacred ſyllable; and when</l>
                  <l>I've done't a thouſand times, begin agen!</l>
                  <l>That Name who honours not, Oh may he be</l>
                  <l>O'rewhelm'd with never-dying infamie!</l>
                  <l>His bleſſed Memorie who adoreth not,</l>
                  <l>Oh may he be eternally forgot!</l>
                  <l>Thy book, my friend (if I do not miſtake)</l>
                  <l>Will pleaſe and ſell for Great GUSTAVUS ſake.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>STEPHEN JONES, <hi>of</hi> S. Johns <hi>Coll.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:8"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16773:8"/>
                  <head>THE BATTELL OF LYPSICH.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ave you not heard the ever-reſtleſſe <hi>Ocean</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Beat on the ſhore with waves continuall motion,</l>
                     <l>Which fill our eares with ſad and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m'ring tones;</l>
                     <l>Juſt like the dolefull ſighs and hollow grones</l>
                     <l>Of thouſands, that together have conjoyn'd</l>
                     <l>T' expreſſe the ſorrows of a wounded minde,</l>
                     <l>For ſome diſaſtrous <hi>Fate;</hi> perhaps the death</l>
                     <l>Of ſome deare <hi>Prince,</hi> untimely reav'd of breath?</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="2" facs="tcp:16773:9"/>They fill the troubled aire with confuſe cries,</l>
                     <l>Which are reſounded by the trembling skies;</l>
                     <l>Which theſe ſad tunes ſo often do repeat,</l>
                     <l>That now the woodie <hi>Choriſters</hi> forget</l>
                     <l>Their wonted ſtrains, and either ſtand as mute,</l>
                     <l>Or to theſe notes their warbling voices ſuit,</l>
                     <l>The willing aire inſtructing to expreſſe</l>
                     <l>To humane eares ſoul-moving heavineſſe.</l>
                     <l>Sweet <hi>Philomel</hi> now thinks upon her rape</l>
                     <l>And former wrongs; that ſhe may fitly ſhape</l>
                     <l>A tune of lively ſorrow, and make known</l>
                     <l>The grief of others, fully, as her own.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Like this was that amazed time, when firſt</l>
                     <l>Our eares thoſe more then frightfull rumours pierc't,</l>
                     <l>Of great <hi>Guſtavus</hi> diſmall <hi>Fate;</hi> with whom</l>
                     <l>All then did ſeem their hopes and hearts t'intombe;</l>
                     <l>And did expreſſe in ſighs and drouping looks,</l>
                     <l>Sorrow enough t'have fill'd moſt ſpatious <hi>Books:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>You might have read, in thought-diſcov'ring eyes,</l>
                     <l>Volumes of ſad and mournfull <hi>Elegies:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>While <hi>Fame</hi> doth with a thouſand tongues reſound</l>
                     <l>Such trembling murmures, as our hearts do wound.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My fainting <hi>Soul,</hi> not able to ſuſtain</l>
                     <l>So oft redoubled blowes, nor ſuch dire pain,</l>
                     <l>Sunk to the ground: then over all my limbes</l>
                     <l>A frigid ſweat and dewie vapour ſwimmes:</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Death-like</hi> ſleep clos'd up my eyes; and I,</l>
                     <l>As one eternally entranc'd, did lie.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16773:9"/>But then methoughts my <hi>Genius</hi> did appeare,</l>
                     <l>And words of comfort whiſpred in mine eare:</l>
                     <l>Then led my airie <hi>Spirit</hi> by the hand,</l>
                     <l>Through darkſome ſhades, to that <hi>Inferior Land</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Region,</hi> where <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbodied Souls</hi> reſide.</l>
                     <l>There what my fancied thoughts to me deſcri'd,</l>
                     <l>I now prepare unto the <hi>World</hi> in verſe,</l>
                     <l>By favour of the <hi>Muſes,</hi> to rehearſe.</l>
                     <l>Thoſe two ſo bloudie <hi>Battels</hi> there I view'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lypſich</hi> and <hi>Lutzen,</hi> dreadfully renew'd:</l>
                     <l>But now more furious and a greater ire</l>
                     <l>Their bloud-enraged ſpirits did enfire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh that thoſe raptures, which then fill'd my brain,</l>
                     <l>Would burn in my impris'ned <hi>Soul</hi> again;</l>
                     <l>That I might ſo in vivid colours paint</l>
                     <l>Thoſe dreadfull fights, as ſhould make <hi>Mortals</hi> faint</l>
                     <l>With horrour and amaze, and when they reade</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Bloud-beſprinkled</hi> verſe, their hearts ſhould bleed!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Divine <hi>Melpomene,</hi> whoſe chiefeſt glorie</l>
                     <l>Conſiſts in ſounding of a <hi>Tragick</hi> ſtorie;</l>
                     <l>Fill me with vig'rous heat, and for a while</l>
                     <l>Let thy rapt <hi>Furie</hi> guide my iron ſtyle:</l>
                     <l>Send <hi>Virgils Genius</hi> to direct my quill,</l>
                     <l>His grave Majeſtick vein do thou inſtill;</l>
                     <l>Or rather <hi>Lucans,</hi> whoſe ſo loftie rhymes</l>
                     <l>Do beſt befit the <hi>Genius</hi> of theſe times.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But oh! what ſudden numneſſe do I feel</l>
                     <l>To damp my boiling bloud! and now I reel,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16773:10"/>As when an <hi>Epilepſie</hi> doth ſurpriſe</l>
                     <l>Some feeble mortall, and his ſenſes ties:</l>
                     <l>Or, when as the <hi>Cumean Sibyls</hi> breaſt</l>
                     <l>Some dire <hi>Prophetick Spirit</hi> hath poſſeſt;</l>
                     <l>She madly rages, ſtruggles all in vain</l>
                     <l>To ſhake away her Furie-cauſed pain:</l>
                     <l>She raves, ſhe frets, ſhe ſtorms, and tears her hair,</l>
                     <l>Stamps with her feet, and like a <hi>Ghoſt</hi> doth ſtare:</l>
                     <l>Mean while, within her rage-diſtracted ſoul,</l>
                     <l>And troubled thoughts, diſcording <hi>Paſsions</hi> roll.</l>
                     <l>Thus am I rackt, while to my working heart</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Phanſie</hi> doth ſuch jarring thoughts impart.</l>
                     <l>For this to ev'ry <hi>Poet</hi> is enjoyn'd,</l>
                     <l>That he ſhall feel in his impreſſive minde</l>
                     <l>The reall <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Paſsions</hi> of all thoſe,</l>
                     <l>Whom he in verſe preſumeth to diſcloſe.</l>
                     <l>Judge what a world of diſcords circling runne</l>
                     <l>Within my breaſt, like <hi>Atomes</hi> in the Sunne,</l>
                     <l>That croſſe, and meet, and meet, and croſſe agen.</l>
                     <l>So many Paſſions of ſo many men,</l>
                     <l>And ſuch repugning thoughts torment my minde,</l>
                     <l>As when two <hi>Armies</hi> have with furie joyn'd:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rage</hi> and <hi>Revenge</hi> march firſt, with burning <hi>Ire:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dread, Fears,</hi> and <hi>Terrours</hi> make them to retire:</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>Shame,</hi> and <hi>Valour,</hi> with malicious <hi>Hate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Their reinforced <hi>Troups</hi> precipitate:</l>
                     <l>They charge them home: theſe break, and ſcatt'red flie</l>
                     <l>Unto their main <hi>Battalia,</hi> which ſtood nigh.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16773:10"/>Here dire <hi>Deſpair</hi> was ranged, double-rankt</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Furie,</hi> and with <hi>Raſhneſſe</hi> ſtrongly flankt.</l>
                     <l>Theſe and a thouſand more oppugning <hi>Phanſies</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Phebus</hi> in my enraged breaſt advances.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Faint not, my <hi>Muſe,</hi> but with a feareleſſe pace</l>
                     <l>March through the midſt of <hi>Furies,</hi> and out-face</l>
                     <l>Armies of <hi>Terrours,</hi> vengefull <hi>Wrath,</hi> and <hi>Ire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Affrightfull <hi>Death,</hi> devouring <hi>Sword,</hi> and <hi>Fire.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shrink not at all to heare the helliſh jawes</l>
                     <l>Of thundring <hi>Cannons</hi> roar with hideous noiſe,</l>
                     <l>Mixt with a thouſand ſhot, that roughly teare</l>
                     <l>The tender welkin, and affright the eare.</l>
                     <l>Let not their clam'rous ſhouts and confuſe cries,</l>
                     <l>Which ſeem to wound the aire, and pierce the skies,</l>
                     <l>Move thee at all: Let not the yelling noiſe</l>
                     <l>Of ſome half-murdred wights make thee to pauſe,</l>
                     <l>Or draw remorſefull pitie from thy heart:</l>
                     <l>Be like a Rock of ſtone; ſhrink not, nor ſtart:</l>
                     <l>Be as regardleſſe of their ſhrieks and grones,</l>
                     <l>As they themſelves have been to others mones.</l>
                     <l>If to ſuch tender thoughts thou yeeld'ſt, my <hi>Muſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy Martiall <hi>Furie</hi> thou wilt quickly loſe;</l>
                     <l>And none, but fearfull <hi>Mothers,</hi> then will praiſe</l>
                     <l>Thy ſoft-ſtrain'd verſe, and heart-relenting layes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But now a little breathe, my <hi>Muſe,</hi> and heare</l>
                     <l>The plaints of others, ſounded to thy eare.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Nymph Germania</hi> doth her ſelf preſent,</l>
                     <l>With face disfigur'd, and with robes all rent,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16773:11"/>And ſprinkled o're with bloud: her golden locks</l>
                     <l>She tears, and furiouſly her breaſt ſhe knocks;</l>
                     <l>Then wrings her hands, lifts up her woe-ſick eyes:</l>
                     <l>And thus at laſt to the unpitying skies</l>
                     <l>She ſpeaks, Oh heav'ns, how long, how long ſhall we</l>
                     <l>The onely ſubject of your vengeance be;</l>
                     <l>Plagu'd with continuall warre, dire cruelties,</l>
                     <l>A thouſand ſlaughters, and calamities;</l>
                     <l>While miſcreant <hi>Ethnicks,</hi> who deride thy power,</l>
                     <l>Are undiſturb'd, and flouriſh to this houre?</l>
                     <l>The curſed <hi>Pagans</hi> laugh, when they behold</l>
                     <l>How many miſeries on us are roll'd.</l>
                     <l>The barb'rous <hi>Turk</hi> inſults with ſpitefull ſcorn,</l>
                     <l>To ſee us <hi>Chriſtians</hi> by our ſelves ſo torn;</l>
                     <l>And on our bodies thoſe deep wounds to bear,</l>
                     <l>Which he ſo much from us himſelf did fear;</l>
                     <l>To ſee our <hi>Forces</hi> by our ſelves o'return'd,</l>
                     <l>Which having joyn'd, might eaſily have ſpurn'd</l>
                     <l>Him, and his Vaſſall <hi>Kings;</hi> and once again,</l>
                     <l>Like their dire <hi>Scourge,</hi> reſiſtleſſe <hi>Tamerlane,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Have hew'd their <hi>Armies,</hi> as a field of corn,</l>
                     <l>Which is by reaping ſickles quickly ſhorn:</l>
                     <l>And then their <hi>Sultan,</hi> in an Iron grate</l>
                     <l>Shut, like ſome monſtrous Beaſt, ſhould curſe his <hi>Fate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And rail upon his <hi>Grand-Impoſtour-Prophet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That vagabond <hi>Arabian, Mahomet:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then, if courage ſerv'd him, valiantly</l>
                     <l>He might daſh out his wretched brains, and die.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:16773:11"/>Then <hi>Stampoldam</hi> (now his <hi>Imperiall</hi> ſeat,</l>
                     <l>That over-looks the World) with flaming heat</l>
                     <l>Enkindled once, ſhould ſend ſuch direfull ſmoke,</l>
                     <l>As ſhould theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> for ever choak:</l>
                     <l>Then in black clouds enwrapt, the fumes ſhould whirle them,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Devils</hi> to the loweſt hell ſhould hurle them.</l>
                     <l>And thou bloud-ſucking <hi>Tartar,</hi> who of late</l>
                     <l>Proffredſt thine aid, my wounds to aggravate;</l>
                     <l>But wert rejected by that pow'rfull <hi>King,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who his <hi>Commiſsion</hi> from the Heav'ns did bring,</l>
                     <l>To ſcourge me for the ſinnes of me and mine:</l>
                     <l>Doſt thou rejoyce to ſee the <hi>Pow'rs Divine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Inflict ſuch rig'rous <hi>Juſtice</hi> on my <hi>Soil,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe very bowels now with torments broil,</l>
                     <l>And raging <hi>Warre;</hi> like the <hi>Sicylian</hi> Hill,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe vaulted caverns ſulph'rie flames do fill?</l>
                     <l>Thou curſed <hi>Rover,</hi> who doſt ſpend thy dayes</l>
                     <l>In wandring up and down a thouſand wayes;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe cold and barren Climate fears no Warre,</l>
                     <l>Not worth the ſword of any <hi>Conquerer:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ceaſe for to triumph o're my wofull ſtate;</l>
                     <l>Leſt at my pray'rs the <hi>Heav'ns</hi> precipitate</l>
                     <l>A vengeance on thy head, ſhall equalliſe</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Warres</hi> bloudie miſchief and dire cruelties;</l>
                     <l>The dreadfull <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> whoſe pois'nous blaſt</l>
                     <l>Into the grave thouſands at once ſhall caſt;</l>
                     <l>Or pinching <hi>Famine,</hi> whoſe long lingring ſtroke</l>
                     <l>Shall by degrees the vitall ſpirits choak;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:16773:12"/>Or, what thou feareſt moſt, ſome rig'rous froſt</l>
                     <l>Shall ſeiſe upon thy coldly-ſited coaſt,</l>
                     <l>And freez the very aire, that want of breath</l>
                     <l>May make you yeeld unto unſparing Death.</l>
                     <l>But why diſturb I thus my wretched heart,</l>
                     <l>By wiſhing unto others ſuch like ſmart</l>
                     <l>As I now feel? Would this give eaſe to me,</l>
                     <l>Or any whit abate my miſerie?</l>
                     <l>It would. Oh that the All-wiſe Providence</l>
                     <l>Would on theſe Miſcreants ſuch like plagues diſpenſe;</l>
                     <l>That they might roar with their calamities,</l>
                     <l>And with their louder clamours drown the cries</l>
                     <l>Of my diſtreſſed children, whoſe ſad mones</l>
                     <l>Do wound my heart, and pierce the very ſtones!</l>
                     <l>How many thouſand <hi>Mothers</hi> at this time,</l>
                     <l>Within the limits of my wretched clime,</l>
                     <l>Weep without ceaſing, and with ſhrilleſt notes</l>
                     <l>And bitter exclamations tear their throats!</l>
                     <l>How many tender <hi>Widows</hi> curſe their <hi>Fates,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By raging Warre robb'd of their deareſt <hi>Mates!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>How many aged <hi>Fathers</hi> lift their eyes</l>
                     <l>Drown'd o're with tears, to the unpitying skies,</l>
                     <l>Admiring that the fulgent Sunne diſplayes</l>
                     <l>On their ſo wretched Land his cheerfull rayes!</l>
                     <l>Is there no pitie in the heav'ns at all?</l>
                     <l>Cannot the grief of Mortals once appall</l>
                     <l>You <hi>Spirits</hi> divine, that 'bove us do reſide,</l>
                     <l>And the rapt Spheres do in their courſes guide?</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:16773:12"/>They wonder that the rolling ſtarres ſtill ſhine,</l>
                     <l>And never at their torments do repine.</l>
                     <l>If their dire imprecations might prevail,</l>
                     <l>They would have had them muffled in a vail</l>
                     <l>Of mournfull hue, and in a pitchie cloud</l>
                     <l>Swoln bigge with tears their heav'nly luſtre ſhroud;</l>
                     <l>That with their hearts the whole earth might agree,</l>
                     <l>And once again a confus'd <hi>Chaos</hi> be.</l>
                     <l>Who can theſe blame that thus exceſſive mone,</l>
                     <l>Who have been ſpoiled of more lives then one;</l>
                     <l>That in ſo ſhort a time (alas!) have loſt</l>
                     <l>That which ſo many cares and yeares hath coſt?</l>
                     <l>Ceaſe, ceaſe, my Children: your ſo wofull crie</l>
                     <l>Will make my ſwelling heart in ſunder flie.</l>
                     <l>Who can endure ſuch ſhrieks as pierce my eares?</l>
                     <l>Who can, unmoved, view ſuch flouds of teares?</l>
                     <l>I dare not upward lift my fainting eyes,</l>
                     <l>Leſt they deſcrie new woes, new miſeries:</l>
                     <l>For whereſoe're I turn me to behold,</l>
                     <l>My cities are in flames and ſmoke enroll'd.</l>
                     <l>Huge heaps of Ruines, Warres dire <hi>Monuments,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cruell <hi>Bellona</hi> every where preſents.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All this great miſchief and diſaſtrous woe</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Rome,</hi> as from a pois'nous ſpring, doth flow.</l>
                     <l>And thou, proud <hi>Frier,</hi> whoſe ambitiouſneſſe</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Triple Diadem</hi> can ſcarce depreſſe;</l>
                     <l>Thrice curſed be thy deadly pride, that thus</l>
                     <l>With warres and ruines haſt o'rewhelmed us.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16773:13"/>Moſt flintie-breaſted Tigre, that canſt brook,</l>
                     <l>With heart unpitying, and unmoved look,</l>
                     <l>To ſee ſo many at thy feet to die,</l>
                     <l>And fall lower then hell, to keep thee high!</l>
                     <l>To ſee ſo many <hi>Nations</hi> choiſeſt flowers</l>
                     <l>Cut down by ſudden death, in ſo few houres!</l>
                     <l>And all this will not move thee to relent,</l>
                     <l>Nor winne thee to revoke thy proud intent.</l>
                     <l>Thy Predeceſſours <hi>Chriſtians</hi> could enflame</l>
                     <l>With courage, to a warre of better fame:</l>
                     <l>'Gainſt <hi>Saracens</hi> t' advance their warlike bands,</l>
                     <l>And to reconquer from thoſe <hi>Pagans</hi> hands</l>
                     <l>Captiv'd <hi>Judea,</hi> and the <hi>Diadem</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of weeping and forlorn <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Surely theſe <hi>Infidels</hi> accurſed <hi>Tribe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Do covertly with ſome rich preſents bribe</l>
                     <l>Thy avarice, that by thy deviliſh art</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Chriſtian</hi> unitie thou mightſt diſpart.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Time</hi> will deſcrie the truth, and Heav'ns juſt Power</l>
                     <l>Will on thy head (I hope) juſt vengeance ſhowre.</l>
                     <l>Here, with a ſigh, as if her ſoul were preſt</l>
                     <l>To flie away, her mournfull ſpeech ſhe ceas'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then did I turn mine eyes about, to ſee</l>
                     <l>Whoſe part was next in this ſad <hi>Tragedie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>LYPSICH,</hi> that fatall town, did then appeare,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe walls &amp; tow'rs trembled, methoughts, with fear,</l>
                     <l>As if ſome aguiſh earthquake now did ſtrive</l>
                     <l>Her very bowels piece-meal for to rive.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16773:13"/>Surely there was juſt cauſe of horrid fear,</l>
                     <l>So many <hi>Furies</hi> being now ſo neare,</l>
                     <l>Who threatned had to trample under feet</l>
                     <l>All that their armed <hi>Rage</hi> could finde or meet.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Upon a ſpatious plain, that did preſent</l>
                     <l>Unto the eye a ſmooth and large extent,</l>
                     <l>Two <hi>Armies</hi> ſtood, marſhall'd in fair aray,</l>
                     <l>Their waving Colours to the winde diſplay:</l>
                     <l>Their well-contrived Ranks yet even were,</l>
                     <l>Their Files compleatly ſtraight, their Battels ſquare:</l>
                     <l>Their equall ſpears, their weapons gliſtring bright</l>
                     <l>Did yeeld, methoughts, a dreadfull-pleaſing ſight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Here the Renowned Great <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> ſtands,</l>
                     <l>Strongly environ'd with thoſe warlike Bands,</l>
                     <l>Which the cold Region of the <hi>North</hi> had ſent,</l>
                     <l>And unto them ſuch hardned bodies lent,</l>
                     <l>As, like the roughneſſe of their native <hi>Soil,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cannot be broken with laborious toil.</l>
                     <l>The big-bon'd <hi>Lappians,</hi> who with nimble pace</l>
                     <l>The ſwifteſt and the wildeſt beaſts can chaſe:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe precious skinnes and furres of richeſt price</l>
                     <l>They ſend abroad for rareſt merchandiſe.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Finlanders</hi> were there, who, clad in buffe,</l>
                     <l>Did think their ſturdie limbes arm'd proof enough:</l>
                     <l>Better to wound their foes they were prepar'd,</l>
                     <l>Then to defend, or ſtand upon their guard.</l>
                     <l>The warlike <hi>Goths,</hi> once of renowned <hi>Fame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe <hi>Anceſtours</hi> with fire and ſword did tame</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16773:14"/>Great <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, and her uſurped crown</l>
                     <l>Snatcht from her head, and proudly trampled down;</l>
                     <l>Making her fields to drink the bloud that flow'd</l>
                     <l>From her own children, who in heaps were ſtrow'd</l>
                     <l>Upon the crimſon-ſtained ground. Their ſteel</l>
                     <l>The ſunne-burnt <hi>Spaniards</hi> too did deadly feel:</l>
                     <l>Within whoſe barren and ſcorcht <hi>Territorie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>There ſtill remain ſome Enſignes of their glorie.</l>
                     <l>Here were they now, and ſeemed to reclaim</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Predeceſſours</hi> long-obſcured <hi>Fame.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And here were troups of <hi>Vandals</hi> ſeen, that made</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Ancient</hi> World ev'n of their <hi>Name</hi> afraid;</l>
                     <l>And had as many Kingdomes over-runne</l>
                     <l>Almoſt, as doth the all-incircling <hi>Sunne.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thoſe that inhabit neare the <hi>Dofrine</hi> Hills,</l>
                     <l>From whoſe cold tops the ſnow continuall drills,</l>
                     <l>Had to this <hi>Battell</hi> ſent an armed Troup,</l>
                     <l>That ſcorn'd at dangers once to ſhrink or ſtoup.</l>
                     <l>The duskie-colour'd <hi>Swethes</hi> ſtood next their <hi>King,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who now had made their wondred <hi>Name</hi> to ring</l>
                     <l>Through fartheſt Regions, which ſo long a time</l>
                     <l>Had ſeem'd congealed with their frozen clime.</l>
                     <l>Here likewiſe might you other <hi>Nations</hi> finde,</l>
                     <l>Drawn by the vigour of a Martiall minde:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iriſh, French, Engliſh,</hi> and the hardie <hi>Scot,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe noted valour ne're will be forgot.</l>
                     <l>There likewiſe were the <hi>German-Saxons</hi> ſeen,</l>
                     <l>Who heretofore aſmuch renown'd had been,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:16773:14"/>As th' ancient <hi>Goths,</hi> or the advent'rous <hi>Gaul,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That did ſo oft the <hi>Romane</hi> Hoſts appall.</l>
                     <l>Such was their number, that ev'n they alone</l>
                     <l>As a full <hi>Armie</hi> might themſelves have ſhown.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oppos'd to theſe, an <hi>Armie</hi> as compleat</l>
                     <l>For fair proportion, and full out as great,</l>
                     <l>Preſents its dreadfull Front, that ſeem'd to breathe</l>
                     <l>Nought leſſe then ruines, wounds, and ſpeedie death.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tillie,</hi> whom long experience in the warre</l>
                     <l>Had often taught to be a <hi>Conquerer,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Did range theſe <hi>Troups;</hi> and, as he thought, ſo right,</l>
                     <l>And in ſo firm a poſture, that they might</l>
                     <l>With eaſe o'recome their undervalu'd <hi>Foes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who now were marching on to meet their blowes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>'T was vain with long orations to delay</l>
                     <l>Their burning courage, which could brook no ſtay.</l>
                     <l>Like two vaſt Woods, whoſe waving tops do dance</l>
                     <l>With gentle windes, theſe mightie Hoſts advance.</l>
                     <l>The very luſtre that their arms did caſt,</l>
                     <l>Would have a coward kill'd with lightning blaſt:</l>
                     <l>But to a <hi>Souldiers</hi> eye not any fight</l>
                     <l>Could be preſented, that would more delight</l>
                     <l>His loftie ſprite. And look how <hi>Sols</hi> bright beams,</l>
                     <l>By art redoubled, kindle burning ſtreams:</l>
                     <l>So the refracted rayes of fulgent ſteel</l>
                     <l>Make <hi>Souldiers</hi> hearts new burning courage feel.</l>
                     <l>Scarce can the fierie <hi>Steeds</hi> endure the ground,</l>
                     <l>Now that they heare the echoing Trumpet ſound:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:16773:15"/>They champ their curbing bits, and proudly neigh,</l>
                     <l>Vext that their maſters do their <hi>Furie</hi> ſtay.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Footmen</hi> fain would double their ſlow pace,</l>
                     <l>But that they fear their order to diſplace.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now is the <hi>Signall</hi> given: with a ſhout</l>
                     <l>As loud as thunder, all the warlike Rout</l>
                     <l>Do make the aire and fields adjacent ring.</l>
                     <l>Then to a charged <hi>Cannon Swethlands King</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Gave fire: ſtraight doth the ſwift-wing'd bullet flie</l>
                     <l>Unto their foes with a rough <hi>Embaſsie;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in ſo high a tone delivers it,</l>
                     <l>As might ſo great a <hi>King</hi> as him befit;</l>
                     <l>Speaking like awfull thunder, whoſe dread ſound</l>
                     <l>Our eares amazes, and our hearts doth wound.</l>
                     <l>To ſecond this, were other bullets ſent</l>
                     <l>From fired <hi>Cannons,</hi> that ſo rudely rent</l>
                     <l>The firſt front of their Battell, that you might</l>
                     <l>See their fair order now diſmangled quite:</l>
                     <l>And like a confus'd heap it doth appeare,</l>
                     <l>Till reſuppli'd by the advancing Rear.</l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>Imperials</hi> are not ſlack, but roundly they</l>
                     <l>With anſw'ring ſhot their former loſſe repay:</l>
                     <l>A Rank of <hi>Cannons,</hi> all at once enfir'd,</l>
                     <l>Did preſently attain their mark deſir'd.</l>
                     <l>The angrie <hi>Swethes</hi> their helliſh furie feel,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe rough encounter made them more then reel;</l>
                     <l>It makes a ſpatious breach, and the weak wall</l>
                     <l>Of bodies batt'red piece-meal now doth fall</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16773:15"/>In ruin'd heaps, and with a crimſon juice,</l>
                     <l>That like a torrent flow'd, the ground embrews.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Help me, my tragick <hi>Muſe,</hi> infuſe new ſtrains,</l>
                     <l>And re-infire my quite amazed Brains.</l>
                     <l>Methinks I feel my vigour to relent,</l>
                     <l>Stricken with horrour and aſtoniſhment,</l>
                     <l>To think upon thoſe direfull ſlaughters, when</l>
                     <l>Thoſe helliſh Engines did ſo many men</l>
                     <l>Diſmangle in a trice, and with a blaſt</l>
                     <l>Their noble ſouls from their ſtout bodies caſt.</l>
                     <l>Here a brave <hi>Captain,</hi> as he fairly ſtands,</l>
                     <l>With words encouraging his warlike Bands,</l>
                     <l>His head ſnatcht off among them flies, and there</l>
                     <l>Speaks in a language now of dread and fear.</l>
                     <l>Here, as another waves his ſword on high,</l>
                     <l>To dare his foe, a fierie Ball doth flie</l>
                     <l>Full in his face, and makes him with a daſh</l>
                     <l>With his own ſword himſelf in ſunder ſlaſh.</l>
                     <l>There ſtood another, who enrag'd did breathe</l>
                     <l>Againſt his Foes revengefull threats of death:</l>
                     <l>But as his words yet in the aire did flie,</l>
                     <l>A double <hi>Cannon</hi> makes a loud replie,</l>
                     <l>And with a greater anger farre did ſtrive</l>
                     <l>His words again into his throat to drive:</l>
                     <l>What he in vain had threatned to his Foes,</l>
                     <l>Makes his own Souldiers feel by reverſt blowes:</l>
                     <l>His ſhiv'red skull and arms all ſhatt'red flew</l>
                     <l>Backward, and ſome that ſtood too neare him ſlew.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16773:16"/>Here one, whom ſome great ſhot affrighted, ſhrunk;</l>
                     <l>But all in vain: upon his armed trunk</l>
                     <l>The ſwift-wing'd Bullet lights; and from his heart,</l>
                     <l>With fear and wounds, his ſoul at once doth ſtart.</l>
                     <l>A rank of Brothers and neare friends here ſtood,</l>
                     <l>Never more true then now alli'd in bloud,</l>
                     <l>Rent by the furie of two Culverings,</l>
                     <l>That arms from ſhoulders, heads from bodies flings;</l>
                     <l>Then altogether mixt them in a Maſſe,</l>
                     <l>And with their Limbes ſtrowes the diſcolour'd graſſe.</l>
                     <l>Some <hi>Demicannons</hi> 'mong a troup of Horſe</l>
                     <l>Did likewiſe ſhew their cruel murd'ring force.</l>
                     <l>Their Iron Cuirace was of ſmall avail:</l>
                     <l>Corſlets of Steel and Coats of well-wrought Mail</l>
                     <l>Could not divert the furie of ſuch ſtrokes,</l>
                     <l>As would have ſtricken down the talleſt oaks,</l>
                     <l>That in the <hi>Caledonian</hi> woods are found,</l>
                     <l>Or ſpread their roots in the <hi>Hercinian</hi> ground.</l>
                     <l>Some Riders wounded are, while th'untoucht Horſe,</l>
                     <l>Feeling his reins now ſlack, with all his force</l>
                     <l>Kicks, flings, and ſtarts untill his Maſter reels;</l>
                     <l>Then, moſt ingratefull, ſpurns him with his heels.</l>
                     <l>Sometime the terrour of the ſhot doth light</l>
                     <l>Upon the Horſe; the Rider ſcapes not quite:</l>
                     <l>For though the bullet ſpare him, yet his Steed</l>
                     <l>Ne're reſts, till of his troubling burden freed:</l>
                     <l>Then caſts him on the clotted ſand, and ſtraight</l>
                     <l>Beginning for to ſink, with all his weight,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:16773:16"/>O're him that erſt he bore he now falls over,</l>
                     <l>And him that rid him once he now doth cover:</l>
                     <l>To him his back afforded once a room,</l>
                     <l>And now his bodie makes for him a tombe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Brave Sp'rits, but too (alas!) unfortunate,</l>
                     <l>How doth my <hi>Muſe</hi> lament your unfit <hi>Fate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Snatcht by thoſe dev'liſh Engines fierie force,</l>
                     <l>That murders without mercie or remorſe;</l>
                     <l>That cut you off at one diſaſtrous blow,</l>
                     <l>Ere that you could your fearleſſe faces ſhow</l>
                     <l>Unto your Enemies, and make them feel</l>
                     <l>Some mortall ſtrokes from your ſharp-edged ſteel!</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Curſt be that Hell-ſprung wit, that did deviſe</l>
                     <l>This fierie Engine, whoſe dire Batteries</l>
                     <l>Scorn all reſiſting force that can be tri'd,</l>
                     <l>And moſt approved valour do deride;</l>
                     <l>That humane bodies rend like fields of corn,</l>
                     <l>Which by the cutting ſithe are quickly ſhorn;</l>
                     <l>Not ſo content, but all-diſmangled daſh them,</l>
                     <l>And in a thouſand confus'd pieces paſh them:</l>
                     <l>Here making one, with his disſhatt'red Head</l>
                     <l>His beſt and deareſt friend to ſtrike ſtark dead.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Renowned <hi>Archimede</hi> of <hi>Syracuſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who by an Engine of thine own didſt bruiſe</l>
                     <l>Thouſands of foes at once; when from a Tower</l>
                     <l>Whole loads of ſtones upon their heads did ſhowre:</l>
                     <l>Thy rare invention now may ſeem a toy,</l>
                     <l>Compar'd with this, which doth farre more deſtroy</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:16773:17"/>At further diſtance; and, like dreadfull thunder,</l>
                     <l>Hath often killed ſome with fear and wonder.</l>
                     <l>But thee poſteritie ſhall ever praiſe,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe thy new device thou didſt not blaze</l>
                     <l>To after-times; but didſt at firſt intend</l>
                     <l>That with thy life the ſame ſhould have an end.</l>
                     <l>But now againſt that more then hated Name,</l>
                     <l>From whom this ſulphurie invention came,</l>
                     <l>Let ev'ry <hi>Age</hi> their furie ſo enlarge,</l>
                     <l>As volleys of dire curſes to diſcharge:</l>
                     <l>Let brimſtone burn his odious brains; let ſmoke</l>
                     <l>His very memorie for ever choak.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By this time did the <hi>Armies</hi> nearer preaſſe:</l>
                     <l>The thundring <hi>Cannons</hi> for a while did ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>And gave permiſſion to th' enraged bands</l>
                     <l>To trie the vigour of their eager hands.</l>
                     <l>Then both at once impetuouſly do ruſh,</l>
                     <l>And 'gainſt each other feircely counterpuſh:</l>
                     <l>As when two Seas againſt each other roam,</l>
                     <l>And break their billowes into ſpatt'red foam;</l>
                     <l>Making the aire to tremble, and the ſhore</l>
                     <l>With dreadfull ſounds and frequent <hi>Echoes</hi> roar:</l>
                     <l>Such was the noiſe, when theſe two Hoſts did cloſe,</l>
                     <l>And made the aire to ring with ſtrokes and blowes.</l>
                     <l>Now Piſtols, Muſquets, and Caliver play:</l>
                     <l>Through fire and ſmoke they finde themſelves a way.</l>
                     <l>No ſhot falls now amiſſe: in this cloſe fight,</l>
                     <l>The random-guided Bullets ſurely light,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:16773:17"/>And drench themſelves in bloud: no armour here</l>
                     <l>Can ſtop their force, which is by much too neare.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now forward on the cloſe-rankt Pikes advance</l>
                     <l>With ſteadie arm, and fearleſſe countenance,</l>
                     <l>Shaking their pointed ſpears, which in the breaſt</l>
                     <l>Of their encountring foes do quickly reſt.</l>
                     <l>Here was true Furie ſeen and val'rous Spight;</l>
                     <l>To which if you compare the other fight,</l>
                     <l>It well might ſeem but Sport, or Play at moſt:</l>
                     <l>When as the ſhot at diſtance doth accoaſt</l>
                     <l>The unſeen Foe, and as it were by chance,</l>
                     <l>Guided at randome, at the mark doth glance:</l>
                     <l>While fierie flaſhes and thick clouds of ſmoke</l>
                     <l>Do blinde their eyes, and the pure aire do choak;</l>
                     <l>Preventing them from ſeeing of their foe,</l>
                     <l>And who it was that gave their mortall blow.</l>
                     <l>Nor here can any one with ſhining blade</l>
                     <l>Revenge the death of his ſlain <hi>Camerade:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But all their vengefull ſplene they do at large,</l>
                     <l>And at adventure, in the aire diſcharge.</l>
                     <l>But 'mong the ſturdie Pikes 'twas otherwiſe:</l>
                     <l>Their Furie is directed by their eyes:</l>
                     <l>And at the ſight of their enraged foe,</l>
                     <l>Redoubled courage in their hearts did flow.</l>
                     <l>Here were two Captains met; with pike and targe,</l>
                     <l>Like furious Rammes, they do each other charge;</l>
                     <l>Till at the laſt the thorough-piercing ſteel</l>
                     <l>Made one of them begin to faint and reel:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:16773:18"/>His valour doth outlive his ſtrength; for ſo,</l>
                     <l>When now he cannot wound his conqu'ring foe,</l>
                     <l>Forward he falls; that he may ne're be found</l>
                     <l>To have ſhrunk back, or yeelded any ground.</l>
                     <l>Then being down, threatnings in vain doth breathe;</l>
                     <l>Calls on his ſouldiers to revenge his death:</l>
                     <l>Who, fir'd with ſhame and rage, with one joynt puſh</l>
                     <l>The ſhort-ſurviving Conquerer o'reruſh.</l>
                     <l>He falls upon his foe, whom but of late</l>
                     <l>With ſteadie ſpear his arm did penetrate.</l>
                     <l>Now with loud ſhouts and vengefull cries, they rear</l>
                     <l>Their angrie ſpirits farre above all fear:</l>
                     <l>Full on the points of ſpears they forward runne:</l>
                     <l>There is not one that wounds or death doth ſhunne.</l>
                     <l>Now had they rais'd within a little while,</l>
                     <l>Over theſe Chieftains corps a fun'rall pile</l>
                     <l>Of ſlaughtred bodies: For it ſeem'd they meant</l>
                     <l>Their Captains ſhould not want a <hi>Monument.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Two brave <hi>Conductours</hi> here brought on their bands,</l>
                     <l>To trie the vigour of their hearts and hands.</l>
                     <l>The valour of their ſouldiers they excite</l>
                     <l>Not now with words, but with exampled fight.</l>
                     <l>Had you but ſeen two Bulls in furie meet,</l>
                     <l>Spurning the yellow ſand with angrie feet;</l>
                     <l>And forward then with headlong force to ruſh,</l>
                     <l>Till that their horns do make the blood to guſh</l>
                     <l>From many wounds, and their black-ſpeckled Hide</l>
                     <l>By this be with another colour di'd:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16773:18"/>Then might you have conjectur'd, with what ſpight</l>
                     <l>And burning rage theſe two brave Souldiers fight.</l>
                     <l>This on his ſword relies, with it doth hew</l>
                     <l>And nimbly cut the others ſpear in two.</l>
                     <l>But he as lightly from his ſide doth ſnatch</l>
                     <l>A readie piſtoll, which did over-match</l>
                     <l>His neare-hand-threatning ſword, and in a trice</l>
                     <l>Quite through his breaſt the fire-ſent bullet flies.</l>
                     <l>See! here another with his ſtretcht-out pike</l>
                     <l>Quite through the bodie of his foe doth ſtrike:</l>
                     <l>But ere he back again the ſame could pluck,</l>
                     <l>He with another through the heart is ſtruck.</l>
                     <l>And now his vanquiſht foe with joyfull eye</l>
                     <l>Beholds his <hi>Victour</hi> on the ground to lie.</l>
                     <l>There might you ſee a noble-courag'd <hi>Swethe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Advance himſelf without all fear of death:</l>
                     <l>His furious ire made him alone intend</l>
                     <l>To kill and wound, not caring to defend.</l>
                     <l>A big-bon'd <hi>Germane</hi> meets him at the point,</l>
                     <l>And with their ſpears they ruſh ſo equall joint,</l>
                     <l>That both at once were wounded, both withall</l>
                     <l>Began to ſink, and both at once did fall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not farre from hence you might have ſeen a crew</l>
                     <l>Of ſturdie lads, that thruſt, and hack, and hew.</l>
                     <l>An <hi>Enſigne</hi> they had ſlain; but could not yet</l>
                     <l>Into their hands his waving colours get.</l>
                     <l>Oft had they ſtoupt to take them from the ground:</l>
                     <l>But from their foes ſuch hindrance ſtill they found,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:16773:19"/>Who doubled on their heads ſuch frequent blowes,</l>
                     <l>That look who ſtoupt, again he never roſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now was the furie of the fight grown hot,</l>
                     <l>The aire reſounded with their frequent ſhot.</l>
                     <l>Fair <hi>Victorie</hi> on both their Hoſts doth gaze,</l>
                     <l>And doth behold their courage with amaze:</l>
                     <l>Now theſe obſerves, then thoſe again beheld;</l>
                     <l>Knowes not as yet to which her ſelf to yeeld:</l>
                     <l>Like to ſome novice <hi>Virgin,</hi> whom a Crew</l>
                     <l>Of am'rous <hi>Youths</hi> with eager ſuits purſue;</l>
                     <l>Her minde from fixing for a while ſhe drawes,</l>
                     <l>And yet delights on ev'ry one to pauſe;</l>
                     <l>Denies not any, yeeldeth unto none:</l>
                     <l>To all alike het equall love is ſhown.</l>
                     <l>Have you not ſeen a field of yellow wheat,</l>
                     <l>Upon whoſe tops ſome gentle windes do beat?</l>
                     <l>They ſeem to bend, and backward for a while,</l>
                     <l>Compell'd by force, they orderly recoil:</l>
                     <l>Then reaſſuming vigour, with a blaſt</l>
                     <l>They bend themſelves forward again in haſte:</l>
                     <l>Such was the manner of theſe warlike Forces,</l>
                     <l>Who ſeem'd to charge with interchanging courſes.</l>
                     <l>Now forward ruſht the <hi>Swethlanders:</hi> anon</l>
                     <l>They back retire: th' <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> come on,</l>
                     <l>And with ſuch furie charge them, as if they</l>
                     <l>At that encounter would have wonne the day.</l>
                     <l>But finding good reſiſtance, this their heat</l>
                     <l>Is quickly cool'd, and backward they retreat.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:16773:19"/>The <hi>Swethes</hi> and <hi>Almains</hi> now with doubled might</l>
                     <l>Renew the vigour of this bloudie fight;</l>
                     <l>March o're the bellies of their ſlaughtred foes,</l>
                     <l>And ſtrictly preaſſe them with unſparing blowes.</l>
                     <l>But here a <hi>Regiment,</hi> in this their Rage,</l>
                     <l>Fearing themſelves too farre for to engage</l>
                     <l>Among their circling enemies, did ſound</l>
                     <l>A fair retreat, and yeeld their conqu'red ground.</l>
                     <l>Thus did the well-experienc'd <hi>Swethes,</hi> who knew</l>
                     <l>When to retire, and when they might purſue.</l>
                     <l>They did not their rough charges here perform,</l>
                     <l>Like to the rage of ſome unguided ſtorm;</l>
                     <l>Or like the furie of an headleſſe, rude,</l>
                     <l>Confuſed, and diſord'red multitude:</l>
                     <l>But as one bodie, with ſo many hands</l>
                     <l>Move all at once, obeying the commands</l>
                     <l>Of one <hi>Conductour,</hi> who, ev'n as a <hi>Soul,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Theſe <hi>Organs</hi> doth direct, guide, and controll.</l>
                     <l>It is not <hi>Furie,</hi> nor a fearleſſe <hi>Heart,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That winnes the day; but <hi>Valour</hi> mixt with <hi>Art.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This did the <hi>Saxons</hi> finde, who now begun</l>
                     <l>Diſorderly to waver, and to ſhunne</l>
                     <l>The rage of their approaching foe, who farre</l>
                     <l>Did them excell in diſcipline of warre;</l>
                     <l>And had in often combatings and fights</l>
                     <l>Learn'd many Martiall Stratagems and ſlights.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Long did the <hi>Saxon</hi> Troups ſtiffely ſuſtain</l>
                     <l>Their rough encounter, and a while maintain</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:16773:20"/>The Conqueſt doubtfull. Their diſmangled bands</l>
                     <l>They fill again with other fighting hands;</l>
                     <l>Advancing forward with a fearleſſe face,</l>
                     <l>Each ſtriving to defend his fellows place,</l>
                     <l>Who at his feet did now half-murdred lie,</l>
                     <l>Staining the verdant graſſe with crimſon die.</l>
                     <l>But ſtill their foes preſt on, who too well knew</l>
                     <l>The leaſt advantage gained to purſue.</l>
                     <l>Then did they ſtagger, and ſcarce willing are</l>
                     <l>Their ſhatt'red ranks and order to repair;</l>
                     <l>But flying back in heaps, by force and fear</l>
                     <l>They break the ranges of their troups in Rear.</l>
                     <l>Words now and threatnings are of ſmall avail:</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Duke</hi> himſelf could not as then prevail</l>
                     <l>With fair entreatings, nor with rough commands,</l>
                     <l>To ſtay the flight of his diſſcatt'red bands.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where flie you <hi>Cowards?</hi> Think you thus to ſhunne</l>
                     <l>The ſlaughtring ſword? You cannot ſure out-runne</l>
                     <l>The nimble horſe, who now without all trouble</l>
                     <l>Will cut you off, and tread you down like ſtubble.</l>
                     <l>Turn, turn again; once more your forces trie:</l>
                     <l>Stand to your arms; this is the way to flie</l>
                     <l>From threatning dangers. Boldly your breaſts oppoſe,</l>
                     <l>And not your backs to your encountring foes.</l>
                     <l>See! the brave <hi>Swethes</hi> ſtill fairly ſtand in range,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet for fear or dread will breake or change.</l>
                     <l>Shall we forſake them, that have come thus farre</l>
                     <l>To undertake for us this dang'rous warre?</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:16773:20"/>The world will brand us with eternall ſhame,</l>
                     <l>And after-Ages will deride our Name.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Fear made them deaf; and now their <hi>Princes</hi> words</l>
                     <l>Are drown'd with noiſe of ſhot and clatt'ring ſwords.</l>
                     <l>They flie in heaps and quite diſord'red ranks,</l>
                     <l>Like to ſome floud that hath born down his banks.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tillie</hi> rejoycing at ſo wiſht a ſight,</l>
                     <l>Beholding half his enemies in flight,</l>
                     <l>Spake thus inſulting; Courage, heartie <hi>Blades,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My noble <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and brave <hi>Camerades:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The day is ours: let theſe baſe <hi>Cowards</hi> flie,</l>
                     <l>And now let us theſe other ſquadrons plie;</l>
                     <l>The ſturdie <hi>Swethes,</hi> whoſe <hi>Kings</hi> victorious Name</l>
                     <l>Keeps them from flying, with a forced ſhame:</l>
                     <l>But charge them home, and with unſparing hands</l>
                     <l>Ruſh boldly on their now half-ſtagg'ring Bands.</l>
                     <l>This having ſaid, he, with a ſp'rit as high</l>
                     <l>As theſe his words, among his foes doth flie;</l>
                     <l>Who him receive with courage nothing leſſe,</l>
                     <l>But with a greater ire his rage repreſſe:</l>
                     <l>As when the angrie <hi>Ocean</hi> with a ſhock</l>
                     <l>Strives for to break ſome firmly fixed rock,</l>
                     <l>Which ſtands unmoved, and his ſwelling pride</l>
                     <l>And vain-ſpent Malice ſeemeth to deride;</l>
                     <l>Making his waves, which did ſo raſhly roam,</l>
                     <l>To daſh themſelves into a ſpatt'red foam:</l>
                     <l>Thus was the <hi>Crabats</hi> furie broke in ſunder,</l>
                     <l>Who fell upon the <hi>Swediſh</hi> troups like thunder.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:16773:21"/>And their brave <hi>Gen'rall,</hi> who had thought his ſight</l>
                     <l>Sufficient was his enemies to fright,</l>
                     <l>Scap'd not unwounded: for the leaden ſhowre</l>
                     <l>Fear'd not at all his mortall-feared Power;</l>
                     <l>Though it be ſtill unknown, from whoſe hand came</l>
                     <l>The force that wounded ſo renown'd a Name.</l>
                     <l>'Tis not a ſingle wound that can reſtrain</l>
                     <l>Or check his valour; but enrag'd again</l>
                     <l>With doubled furie, he aſſails his foes,</l>
                     <l>Who will not yeeld him any thing but blowes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By this time great <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> wachfull eye</l>
                     <l>An opportune advantage doth eſpie</l>
                     <l>To break the ſquadrons of their ranged Horſe,</l>
                     <l>Who charged them ſo oft with headlong force.</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Regiment</hi> their ſtations quickly change,</l>
                     <l>And now ſtood ord'red in a treble range:</l>
                     <l>The firſt rank couched on their knees: the next</l>
                     <l>Stood half-way bended: but the third erects</l>
                     <l>His armed trunk upright. Thus as one rank,</l>
                     <l>Were all their muſquets levelled point-blank.</l>
                     <l>At both their wings ſtood troups of readie Horſe,</l>
                     <l>Prepar'd to ſecond with a ſpeedie courſe.</l>
                     <l>Then at a word did all give fire, and powre</l>
                     <l>Among th'enraged Horſe a leaden ſhowre,</l>
                     <l>That flew as thick as hail, when <hi>Boreas</hi> blaſt</l>
                     <l>Doth from the clouds his frozen treaſure caſt.</l>
                     <l>Had I an hundred tongues, an Iron heart,</l>
                     <l>And all the help the <hi>Muſes</hi> can impart;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:16773:21"/>Yet could I not in this my ſtagg'ring verſe</l>
                     <l>The ſhadow of that ſlaughter now rehearſe:</l>
                     <l>When in the twinkling of an eye did fall</l>
                     <l>So many wounded wights, Horſe, Man and all.</l>
                     <l>And that fair <hi>Squadron,</hi> which ſo lately ſtood</l>
                     <l>Like to ſome thick and cloſely-ranged wood,</l>
                     <l>Confuſedly doth now appeare, and ſcatt'red.</l>
                     <l>Their order ſpoil'd, their ranks in ſunder ſhatt'red:</l>
                     <l>As when in <hi>Autumne</hi> ſome tempeſtuous blaſt</l>
                     <l>From half-dead trees their feeble leaves doth caſt,</l>
                     <l>And with another garment then her own</l>
                     <l>The under-ſited ground is thickly ſtrown:</l>
                     <l>Thus was the field with bleeding bodies ſpread,</l>
                     <l>That had been wounded by the piercing lead.</l>
                     <l>But while the reſt, fill'd with amaze and wonder,</l>
                     <l>To ſee th' effects of this ſo ſudden thunder,</l>
                     <l>Knew not which way to turn or bend their faces;</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Regiment</hi> of Horſe with doubled paces</l>
                     <l>Flie in amongſt them; in their teeth diſcharge</l>
                     <l>A ſecond volley; make the breach more large.</l>
                     <l>Then forward on with rage and force they puſh,</l>
                     <l>And their fear-ſtrucken foes ſoon over-ruſh;</l>
                     <l>Who now had loſt all minde and heart to fight,</l>
                     <l>And did betake them to a ſudden flight.</l>
                     <l>This their example made their other Bands</l>
                     <l>Begin to faint, and fight with trembling hands.</l>
                     <l>And as their feeble vigour doth decreaſe,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Swethlanders</hi> doth double: on they preaſſe</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:16773:22"/>With greater courage now, then ere before:</l>
                     <l>The ground doth ſwimme with ſtreams of humane gore.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>At laſt, not able for to fill ſo faſt</l>
                     <l>Their ſlaught'red ranks, as the rough <hi>Swethes</hi> did waſte;</l>
                     <l>Backward they throng in heaps, diſord'red quite,</l>
                     <l>Not willing now nor able for to fight.</l>
                     <l>But while that all tumultuouſly do ſtrive</l>
                     <l>To ſcape away, they do the formoſt drive</l>
                     <l>Headlong before them: over theſe they ſtumble,</l>
                     <l>And ſo the next, and next to them doth tumble.</l>
                     <l>(Strange for to ſee!) here lay a Souldier dead;</l>
                     <l>O're whom an heap of living bodies ſpread.</l>
                     <l>Sure he enjoy'd a farre more noble Tombe,</l>
                     <l>Then thoſe which do th' <hi>Egyptian</hi> Kings inhume;</l>
                     <l>The loftie <hi>Pyramids,</hi> whom loud-tongu'd <hi>Fame</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>One of the world's chief wonders ſtill doth name:</l>
                     <l>Or then that ſo renowned <hi>Sepulchre,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which doth <hi>Mauſolus</hi> Kingly bones interre.</l>
                     <l>All theſe were cov'red with dead marble ſtones:</l>
                     <l>But here is one intomb'd with living bones.</l>
                     <l>The fiery ſteeds, that never mercie knew,</l>
                     <l>Proudly themſelves in ſpatt'red bloud embrew.</l>
                     <l>Here 'gainſt a ſprawling bodie one doth ſpurn,</l>
                     <l>And from his former wounds makes bloud return.</l>
                     <l>Another there a living head doth cruſh,</l>
                     <l>And from the ſame makes bloud and brains to guſh.</l>
                     <l>Meanwhile their maſters with unſparing hands,</l>
                     <l>Now none reſiſt, murder at once whole Bands.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:16773:22"/>And where the ſword doth fail, the trampling horſe</l>
                     <l>Quickly diſpatches with an headlong courſe.</l>
                     <l>The former ſlaughter of this bloudie day,</l>
                     <l>Compar'd with this, might ſeem <hi>Bellona's</hi> play.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Sunne</hi> no longer could endure this ſight,</l>
                     <l>But in compaſſion did withdraw his light:</l>
                     <l>And that he might their further rage prevent,</l>
                     <l>With ſpeedie wings the welcome <hi>Night</hi> he ſent;</l>
                     <l>Who, muffled in a vail of ſable hue,</l>
                     <l>Quite o're the heads of theſe fierce <hi>Victours</hi> flew;</l>
                     <l>And then before them caſteth ſuch a miſt,</l>
                     <l>As made their hands and vengefull Heat deſiſt.</l>
                     <l>So a fierce Lion, a <hi>Getulian</hi> Swain</l>
                     <l>(If antique ſtories do not miſſe, or feigne)</l>
                     <l>Did with his garment muffle o're the head;</l>
                     <l>Then this ſo furious Beaſt did ſtand as dead:</l>
                     <l>Stirres not one jot; but, as amazed quite,</l>
                     <l>Loſes his cruell furie with his ſight:</l>
                     <l>And while that he thus ſtrangely ſeems to pauſe,</l>
                     <l>The fearfull <hi>Swain</hi> ſcapes his devouring jawes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:16773:23"/>
                  <head>THE BATTELL OF LVTZEN.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He hel-born <hi>Furies,</hi> who delight in bloud,</l>
                     <l>And had of late ſwumme in a purple floud,</l>
                     <l>Which not at all their vengefull thirſt abates,</l>
                     <l>Do now again invoke the Pow'rfull <hi>Fates</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To haſten forward ſuch another day,</l>
                     <l>Where they in midſt of fire and ſmoke might play;</l>
                     <l>And with their pois'nous breath and fierie brands</l>
                     <l>Inflame <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> and th' <hi>Imperiall</hi> Bands.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:16773:23"/>The All-diſpoſing Providence above,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe preſence makes the trembling heav'ns to move,</l>
                     <l>Doth yeeld to theſe infernall <hi>Hagges</hi> deſire.</l>
                     <l>Let none preſume a reaſon to require:</l>
                     <l>It was his will; let that alone ſuffice:</l>
                     <l>And ſure 'twas juſt; though that the feeble eyes</l>
                     <l>Of our dimme mortall judgement never can</l>
                     <l>With punctuall knowledge heav'nly actions ſcanne.</l>
                     <l>Weep, mournfull <hi>Germanie;</hi> For once again</l>
                     <l>Thy childrens bloud thy wretched fields muſt ſtain:</l>
                     <l>And to augment thy loſſe, that Pow'rfull <hi>King,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who hopes of peace and victorie did bring,</l>
                     <l>Muſt there receive his mortall wound, with whom</l>
                     <l>Shall thouſands more receive their <hi>Fatall</hi> doom.</l>
                     <l>Thy freedome, which thou haſt ſo long time ſought,</l>
                     <l>Muſt with more ſtreams of humane bloud be bought.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh happie <hi>England,</hi> who wilt ſcarce confeſſe,</l>
                     <l>Drunk with ſecuritie, thy happineſſe;</l>
                     <l>That doſt enjoy ſuch Quietneſſe, ſuch Eaſe,</l>
                     <l>Such calme Tranquillitie, and bleſſed Peace;</l>
                     <l>And that not purchas'd by laborious Toil,</l>
                     <l>By fire, and ſword, by ruine, and by ſpoil;</l>
                     <l>Nor by the loſſe of thy choice <hi>Youth,</hi> whoſe <hi>Fate</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou wouldſt not fear 'gainſt <hi>Heav'n</hi> t'expoſtulate:</l>
                     <l>But it hath coſt thee nothing: for behold,</l>
                     <l>On thee th' Almightie hath his bleſſings roll'd,</l>
                     <l>Without all labour or deſert of thine,</l>
                     <l>Meerly by inſtinct of his love divine;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:16773:24"/>And hath enricht thee with a gracious <hi>King,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>At whoſe bleſt Birth <hi>Angels</hi> of peace did ſing:</l>
                     <l>Oh look upon thy neighbour <hi>Germanie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Drown'd with a floud of tears and miſerie;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe towns are ruin'd, and whoſe Cities burn,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe fields do flow with bloud, whoſe people mourn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Think but on this all you that cannot weep,</l>
                     <l>Who in the arms of happie <hi>Peace</hi> do ſleep.</l>
                     <l>Is't irkſome to your eares? Your tender Heart</l>
                     <l>At theſe moleſting ſounds (methinks) doth ſtart:</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Warres</hi> and <hi>Woes</hi> y' have been ſo long ſecure,</l>
                     <l>That now you cannot their rough Name endure.</l>
                     <l>Are you become like to the <hi>Sybarite,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſoft'ned ſpirit, ſottiſh appetite</l>
                     <l>Could no harſh noiſe endure, nor that ſhrill ſound,</l>
                     <l>That doth from hamm'red Steel and Braſſe rebound?</l>
                     <l>And therefore ſuch <hi>Artificers</hi> as thoſe,</l>
                     <l>That did moleſt their eares with clatt'ring blowes,</l>
                     <l>By a preventing law they did compell</l>
                     <l>Farre off in ſome obſcurer place to dwell.</l>
                     <l>Shall theſe my verſes, that with clatt'ring ding</l>
                     <l>The ſtrokes of Warre and furious Rage do ſing,</l>
                     <l>Diſpleaſe our <hi>Britiſh</hi> eares, who are of late</l>
                     <l>(It ſeems) grown tender and effeminate?</l>
                     <l>Your <hi>Amorettoes</hi> think them farre too rough,</l>
                     <l>Not ſmooth, nor pleaſing, nor half low enough:</l>
                     <l>They cannot ſcrew them any wayes to ſuit</l>
                     <l>Or conſort with their ſweet-tun'd warbling <hi>Lute:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:16773:24"/>They are too loftie for a <hi>Womans</hi> voice,</l>
                     <l>And drown all ſweetneſſe with a ratling noiſe.</l>
                     <l>Some hollow-ſounding <hi>Drumme,</hi> or <hi>Trumpet</hi> ſhrill,</l>
                     <l>Or thundring <hi>Cannons,</hi> that the eare do fill</l>
                     <l>With frightfull ſounds, fit Inſtruments would be</l>
                     <l>To Echo forth my lines melodiouſly.</l>
                     <l>The ſmaller ſhot ſhall ſerve for repetition,</l>
                     <l>While clatt'ring ſwords ſhall repreſent diviſion:</l>
                     <l>And the more <hi>Diſcords</hi> that my verſes ſhow,</l>
                     <l>The better <hi>Harmonie</hi> from thence will flow.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then cheerfully my loftie <hi>Muſe</hi> proceed:</l>
                     <l>There will be ſome that will thy verſes reade;</l>
                     <l>Such gen'rous ſpirits, in whoſe manly breaſts</l>
                     <l>An ardent love of <hi>Fame</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> reſts;</l>
                     <l>Who ſtill retain ſome ſparks of that deſire,</l>
                     <l>Which did their <hi>Anceſtours</hi> brave hearts enfire,</l>
                     <l>When they did make <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Cypriots</hi> feel</l>
                     <l>The direfull force of their reſiſtleſſe ſteel:</l>
                     <l>Or when ſo often, to their laſting glorie,</l>
                     <l>They did o're-runne the <hi>Gallick</hi> Territorie;</l>
                     <l>Or when the <hi>Worlds Diſturber</hi> they did tame,</l>
                     <l>Who <hi>Europes Monarchie</hi> alone doth claim:</l>
                     <l>Such men as theſe will farre above thy merit</l>
                     <l>Approve thy lines, applaud thy loftie ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>That thus haſt choſen with induſtrious brains</l>
                     <l>To ſhew thy vigour in <hi>Heroick</hi> ſtrains;</l>
                     <l>And not in ſoft-tun'd Ditties, or ſuch layes</l>
                     <l>As <hi>Ladies</hi> onely and their ſervants praiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:16773:25"/>
                     <l>The <hi>Sunne</hi> had finiſht now his annuall Race,</l>
                     <l>Since Fatall <hi>Lypſich</hi> with a mournfull face</l>
                     <l>Beheld <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> and his warlike Force</l>
                     <l>Her fertile plains die with a bloudie ſourſe;</l>
                     <l>Which ſcarce as yet fully exhauſt appeares,</l>
                     <l>And ſcarce had <hi>Lypſich</hi> wip'd away her tears,</l>
                     <l>When lo, not farre, upon a neighb'ring plain</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bellona</hi> ſounds her dreadfull trump again:</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Lutzen</hi> is appointed for the ſtage,</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Mars</hi> intends to act a ſecond Rage;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lutzen,</hi> that <hi>Fatall Town,</hi> whoſe very ſound</l>
                     <l>I feel my grief-diſturbed heart to wound.</l>
                     <l>There Great <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> ſo renown'd, became</l>
                     <l>(Dire alteration!) onely now a Name;</l>
                     <l>Once of ſuch power, that his conqu'ring hands</l>
                     <l>Could tame ſtout <hi>Nations,</hi> and ſubdue their Bands.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>CESAR</hi> himſelf would bluſh, and never dare</l>
                     <l>His Conqueſts with <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> to compare.</l>
                     <l>For had he liv'd to ſee what skilfull hands</l>
                     <l>And valiant hearts are in the <hi>Germane</hi> Lands,</l>
                     <l>Who go not naked now, but clad in ſteel,</l>
                     <l>And will not eaſily be made to reel;</l>
                     <l>Sure he had ſtartled, and his conqu'ring courſe</l>
                     <l>Had been prevented by a ſtronger force.</l>
                     <l>Let not black <hi>Envie</hi> then preſume or dare</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> worthie glorie to empair,</l>
                     <l>Who conqu'red had in ſuch a narrow time</l>
                     <l>So many Lands, in ſuch a warlike Clime.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:16773:25"/>Let the Proud <hi>Spaniard</hi> to his laſting ſhame</l>
                     <l>His many Conqueſts of the <hi>Indians</hi> name:</l>
                     <l>And let him boaſt, how many <hi>Millions</hi> too</l>
                     <l>Of unreſiſting People there he ſlew;</l>
                     <l>While a few <hi>Belgian</hi> Merchants in deſpight</l>
                     <l>Of all his Pride, Ambition, Pow'r, and Might,</l>
                     <l>Will not be tamed, nor be made to yeeld,</l>
                     <l>But ſtill affront his <hi>Armies</hi> in the field;</l>
                     <l>Having no Kingdome, but a narrow <hi>State;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet his <hi>Imperiall</hi> Greatneſſe Check and Mate.</l>
                     <l>What Honour then belongs to <hi>Swethlands</hi> King,</l>
                     <l>Who to ſubjection could ſuch Nations bring,</l>
                     <l>That had been ſo inured unto Warres,</l>
                     <l>And ever exercis'd in bloudie Jarres!</l>
                     <l>Had <hi>Mars</hi> himſelf, attended with a Band</l>
                     <l>Of dreadfull <hi>Furies,</hi> entred in their Land;</l>
                     <l>They would have met him with a fearleſſe heart,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhould his <hi>Name</hi> or <hi>Pow'r</hi> have made them ſtart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But whither takes my roving <hi>Muſe</hi> her flight?</l>
                     <l>I muſt not here a <hi>Panegyrick</hi> write,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſpend my ſelf in ſuch admiring laies,</l>
                     <l>As ſound nought elſe but Great GUSTAVUS praiſe.</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Battell</hi> is my ſcope, ſo dire, ſo fierce,</l>
                     <l>That my ſad <hi>Muſe</hi> doth tremble to rehearſe;</l>
                     <l>And ſeeks an hundred ſlights, a while to ſtay</l>
                     <l>The black recitall of this bloudie day:</l>
                     <l>Like to ſome tim'rous Hart, that from the crie</l>
                     <l>Of Hounds and Huntſmen haſtily doth flie:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:16773:26"/>Now here, now there he turns; then back again</l>
                     <l>Breaks through the woods, ſcuds o're the ſpatious plain,</l>
                     <l>And tries a thouſand ſhifts, ere at the laſt</l>
                     <l>Himſelf on hazard of a fight he'l caſt.</l>
                     <l>Thus my ſlow <hi>Muſe</hi> digreſſions doth premiſe,</l>
                     <l>And large preambles (as you ſee) deviſe;</l>
                     <l>Onely to ſtay a while, ere ſhe recite</l>
                     <l>The ſad narration of black <hi>Lutzens</hi> fight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Swethlands</hi> Heroick King his Martiall train</l>
                     <l>Neare <hi>Naumburg</hi> Citie ſpreads upon a plain:</l>
                     <l>Of fighting yet no hopes there did appeare:</l>
                     <l>His purpoſe onely was to march more neare,</l>
                     <l>And joyn his <hi>Forces</hi> with the <hi>Saxon</hi> Bands;</l>
                     <l>That ſo the ſurer with united hands</l>
                     <l>They might to all their foes attempts replie,</l>
                     <l>And not be forc'd coy <hi>Fortunes</hi> grace to trie.</l>
                     <l>'Tis found too deer a bargain in theſe dayes,</l>
                     <l>By valour onely for to purchaſe praiſe.</l>
                     <l>He's valiant now, that winnes the Victorie,</l>
                     <l>Be it by Number, Slight, or Subteltie,</l>
                     <l>By Stratagem, by Cunning, or by Skill,</l>
                     <l>By Courage, Furie, or by what you will.</l>
                     <l>And ſure 'tis vain for an Heroick Breaſt,</l>
                     <l>That will not but on equall terms conteſt;</l>
                     <l>That ſcorns advantages to ſeek, or take,</l>
                     <l>But would that <hi>Valour</hi> ſhould him <hi>Victour</hi> make;</l>
                     <l>While that his ſubtil foe doth ſliely watch</l>
                     <l>All proff'red opportunities to catch,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:16773:26"/>And thinks it no diſgracefull cowardize,</l>
                     <l>To wound or kill him as he ſleeping lies.</l>
                     <l>Might <hi>Valour</hi> of it ſelf alone ſuffice</l>
                     <l>To winne the day in ev'ry enterpriſe,</l>
                     <l>The noble <hi>Swethes</hi> with Great <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> Name</l>
                     <l>Would like the <hi>Macedons</hi> the whole world tame.</l>
                     <l>Think it no wonder, that their Mightie <hi>King,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe preſence onely oft did conqueſts bring,</l>
                     <l>Should notwithſtanding, like to one afraid,</l>
                     <l>Expect, and wiſh, and ſeek for further aid.</l>
                     <l>It was not fear, but Martiall Policie,</l>
                     <l>That made him thus to others help complie.</l>
                     <l>Had he been ever thus, and ne're tranſcended,</l>
                     <l>This temp'rate Vertue had him ſafe defended:</l>
                     <l>He might have liv'd and flouriſht to this houre,</l>
                     <l>And ſtill ſhould <hi>Rome</hi> have feared <hi>Swethlands</hi> Power.</l>
                     <l>But 'tis a wonder that he could ſo rule</l>
                     <l>His burning Sp'rit, and it ſo often cool</l>
                     <l>By mod'rate counſell, checking Policie.</l>
                     <l>Admire who will that he ſo ſoon did die:</l>
                     <l>My ſorrow-ſtrucken <hi>Muſe</hi> admireth more</l>
                     <l>That he ſo vent'rous was not ſlain before.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As now he marches with his valiant Bands,</l>
                     <l>Some ſtragling Pris'ners fell into his hands,</l>
                     <l>Who did aſcertain him, that not one Foe</l>
                     <l>Did of their march and neare approaching know:</l>
                     <l>Not farre off <hi>Wall'nſtein</hi> with th' <hi>Imperiall</hi> Hoſt,</l>
                     <l>Securely lay enquartred in that coaſt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:16773:27"/>Not once ſuppoſing that his Enemie</l>
                     <l>Was in the field, or now had marcht ſo nigh.</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Swethlands</hi> King heard this intelligence,</l>
                     <l>Rapt with exceeding joy, his firſt pretence</l>
                     <l>He changes, now reſolves without more aid</l>
                     <l>His foes thus unexpecting to invade:</l>
                     <l>Then to his Captains ſhews his new intent,</l>
                     <l>Who to his high deſigne gave ſoon conſent.</l>
                     <l>Onely <hi>Knipphauſen</hi> a ſtout <hi>Colonell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And long experienc'd, lik'd it not ſo well:</l>
                     <l>And ſure he did his judgement ſtrictly joyn</l>
                     <l>Unto the rules of modern diſcipline.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The courſe of <hi>Warre</hi> is like a game at Dice;</l>
                     <l>Where Skill with doubtfull <hi>Fortune</hi> mixed lies.</l>
                     <l>It is the ſcope of cunning Management,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fortunes</hi> deceitfull hazards to prevent;</l>
                     <l>And ne're to her blinde Favour once to ſtand,</l>
                     <l>But when compelling accidents command.</l>
                     <l>They that renouncing skill commit their game</l>
                     <l>To unknown <hi>Chance,</hi> deſerve to loſe the ſame.</l>
                     <l>This fickle <hi>Goddeſſe,</hi> that the world ſo fears</l>
                     <l>With doubtfull hazards, ne're more blinde appeares,</l>
                     <l>Then when in Warlike actions and in fight</l>
                     <l>She doth expreſſe her over-ruling Might.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Skill</hi> joynd with <hi>Valour,</hi> and a Pow'rfull <hi>Hoſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Can but the conqueſt promiſe at the moſt.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Victorie</hi> is never ſure till wonne;</l>
                     <l>And none can triumph till the fight be done.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:16773:27"/>The wiſeſt <hi>Captains</hi> in theſe modern dayes</l>
                     <l>Do ſeek to winne the conqueſt by delaies.</l>
                     <l>'Tis no diſgracefull Cowardize to ſtand</l>
                     <l>(Though uncompell'd) on the defenſive hand.</l>
                     <l>It is the ſureſt courſe and ſafeſt held,</l>
                     <l>To ſhunne a <hi>Battell,</hi> but to keep the field.</l>
                     <l>They that can beſt prevent their furious foes,</l>
                     <l>Shall winne the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> without ſtroke or blowes.</l>
                     <l>My noble <hi>Prince,</hi> this is my free advice:</l>
                     <l>But if your Royall will ſhall enterpriſe</l>
                     <l>Some more ſublime deſigne, my heart and hand</l>
                     <l>Shall readily obey your juſt command;</l>
                     <l>And I would ruſh alone through midſt of Foes,</l>
                     <l>Though that a thouſand deaths ſhould counterpoſe.</l>
                     <l>Thus grave <hi>Knipphauſen</hi> ſpake with ſtayed look,</l>
                     <l>And minde unmoved. But the fierie Duke,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bernard</hi> of <hi>Saxon Weimar,</hi> who could ne're</l>
                     <l>Endure the ſhadow of a ſeeming fear;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe burning courage could not brook delayes,</l>
                     <l>His reſolution in ſuch words diſplayes;</l>
                     <l>Now is the wiſhed time, th' expected houre</l>
                     <l>Yeelded to us by Heav'ns diſpoſing Power,</l>
                     <l>That we may now our former-vanquiſht foe</l>
                     <l>Extirpate quite with his laſt overthrow.</l>
                     <l>Their hearts are quail'd alreadie; and ſhall we</l>
                     <l>Want hearts to meet them who deſire to flee?</l>
                     <l>Shall we, that have ſo many <hi>Conqueſts</hi> wonne,</l>
                     <l>So many <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Provinces</hi> o're-runne,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:16773:28"/>Begin to faint, and ſhew we are afraid,</l>
                     <l>And dare not theſe half-ſtagg'ring foes invade?</l>
                     <l>Oh ſhame to think! Could we do more then thus,</l>
                     <l>If they had vanquiſht and quite conquer'd us?</l>
                     <l>Shall we be ſo ingratefull unto Heaven,</l>
                     <l>Who unto us ſuch victories hath given,</l>
                     <l>To make us fearleſſe in ſo juſt a cauſe,</l>
                     <l>And to proceed without demurre or pauſe?</l>
                     <l>Shall we neglect ſo fair and fit occaſion</l>
                     <l>T'aſſail our foes with undeſcri'd invaſion?</l>
                     <l>Long, long we may expect, ere once again</l>
                     <l>The Heav'nly <hi>Fates</hi> ſuch favour will us deigne:</l>
                     <l>And be aſſur'd, that if we do retreat,</l>
                     <l>We quite ſhall damp our ſouldiers vig'rous heat.</l>
                     <l>And make our Enemies become more bold,</l>
                     <l>When they ſhall once our tim'rous march behold.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Theſe words, like oyl pour'd on the greedie fire,</l>
                     <l>Made Great <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> burn with fiercer ire.</l>
                     <l>He gives command, that with the ſwifteſt ſpeed</l>
                     <l>His Royall <hi>Armie</hi> forward ſhould proceed.</l>
                     <l>The hollow-ſounding drumme and trumpet ſhrill</l>
                     <l>The Souldiers eares with cheerfull clamours fill;</l>
                     <l>While with the aire the waving colours play,</l>
                     <l>And by their motion point them out the way.</l>
                     <l>Forward they troup to <hi>Lutzens</hi> bloudie ſoil,</l>
                     <l>And with glad thoughts and hopes the time beguile.</l>
                     <l>Oft did the ſtrictneſſe of th' encloſing way</l>
                     <l>Their haſtie ſpeed and expedition ſtay:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:16773:28"/>Egg'd on with hopes of victorie and ſpoil,</l>
                     <l>They did refuſe no ſweating pains and toil.</l>
                     <l>Had you but ſeen thoſe valiant Bands advance</l>
                     <l>With nimble feet, with cheerfull countenance,</l>
                     <l>And doubled pace, you would have rather gueſs'd</l>
                     <l>That they were haſting to ſome welcome feaſt,</l>
                     <l>Then marching to their grave, which was th' event</l>
                     <l>Of many thouſands that then gladly went.</l>
                     <l>But notwithſtanding all the haſte they made,</l>
                     <l>So many lets and obſtacles delaid</l>
                     <l>Their num'rous Bands, that now the ſetting Sunne</l>
                     <l>Swifter then they his uſuall race had runne,</l>
                     <l>And did begin to drown his ſhining beams</l>
                     <l>Within the <hi>Oceans</hi> vaſt incircling ſtreams.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some troups of horſe that neareſt lay, began</l>
                     <l>To-skirmiſh with the <hi>Swethes</hi> approaching <hi>Vanne,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who with much loſſe of time had lately paſt</l>
                     <l>A narrow bridge, which ſtopt them in their haſte.</l>
                     <l>Theſe light-arm'd <hi>Crabats</hi> firſt of all did feel</l>
                     <l>The deadly force of their victorious ſteel.</l>
                     <l>From them an Enſigne too they did ſurpriſe</l>
                     <l>Depainted with an ominous device;</l>
                     <l>With <hi>happy Fortune,</hi> and <hi>Joves</hi> princely <hi>Fowl,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe <hi>Name</hi> did once the ſpatious world controll.</l>
                     <l>But the <hi>Finlandian Duke</hi> ſo ſmall a prize</l>
                     <l>Beheld with ſad and diſcontented eyes,</l>
                     <l>Griev'd that ſo ſoon the All-endark'ning night</l>
                     <l>Did ſtay their hands, and hide their foes from ſight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:16773:29"/>
                     <l>Once the Dayes <hi>Charioter</hi> his circling pace</l>
                     <l>Vouchſaf'd to ſtop in middle of his race;</l>
                     <l>While <hi>Judahs Champion</hi> with unſparing hands</l>
                     <l>Hew'd down the <hi>Ethnicks</hi> Heav'n-accurſed Bands:</l>
                     <l>But the bleſt name of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> hath a force</l>
                     <l>To winne from heav'n an undeſerv'd remorſe;</l>
                     <l>And that they may ſo great a ſlaughter ſhunne,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sol</hi> his diurnall Race will ſwifter runne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now doth th' <hi>Imperiall Grand Commander</hi> heare</l>
                     <l>Frequent <hi>Alarms</hi> reſounded in his eare:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Poſt</hi> after <hi>Post</hi> are ſent to certifie</l>
                     <l>Of their ſo neare-approaching <hi>Enemie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Here three at once quite ſpent and out of breath,</l>
                     <l>Yet told their mindes by looks as pale as Death.</l>
                     <l>Th' amazed <hi>Duke</hi> ſtartled when he did heare</l>
                     <l>That the bold <hi>Swethes</hi> had gotten now ſo neare:</l>
                     <l>Then frets with anger, when he calls to minde</l>
                     <l>How all his troups lay ſcatt'red and disjoyn'd.</l>
                     <l>'Twas now no time to ſleep, though the moiſt Night</l>
                     <l>The tired ſenſes did to reſt invite.</l>
                     <l>He recollects his ſpirits, and his eyes</l>
                     <l>Up to the Heav'ns he elevateth thrice:</l>
                     <l>At laſt ſpake thus; <hi>Thou Pow'r Omnipotent,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great God of Hoſts, that doſt our Foes prevent;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou All-foreſeeing</hi> Sentinell, <hi>whoſe eye</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Through thickeſt clouds our</hi> Enemies <hi>doth ſpie:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Perpetuall</hi> Glorie <hi>and divineſt</hi> Fame</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Be rendred to thy ever-honour'd</hi> Name,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:16773:29"/>
                        <hi>That thus haſt ſent thy meſſenger of</hi> Night</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To ſtay theſe cruell</hi> Hereticks <hi>from fight,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That 'gainſt all Pietie and humane Lawes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Would trample under feet thy</hi> Cath'lick cauſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This ſaid, he haſtens unto conſultation</l>
                     <l>For beſt directions, and for preparation:</l>
                     <l>He ſends abroad his letters, and commands</l>
                     <l>For quick aſſembling of his ſcatt'red <hi>Bands:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now thinks he on the fitteſt place t'advance</l>
                     <l>His greater Shot and fierie Ordinance.</l>
                     <l>Some Mounts were rais'd alreadie to his hand,</l>
                     <l>Where ſome of <hi>Ceres</hi> airie <hi>Engines</hi> ſtand;</l>
                     <l>But now rough <hi>Mars</hi> doth ſhoulder for the place,</l>
                     <l>And on the ſame his warlike <hi>Engines</hi> trace.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Pioners</hi> had with laborious ſpade</l>
                     <l>About theſe <hi>Batt'ries</hi> ſtrong <hi>Entrenchments</hi> made,</l>
                     <l>To guard them from their foes, who otherwiſe</l>
                     <l>Might with ſome headlong onſet them ſurpriſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Meanwhile did <hi>Swethlands</hi> grieved <hi>King</hi> command</l>
                     <l>His Royall <hi>Armie</hi> on the place to ſtand.</l>
                     <l>Here for a ſpace their Martiall <hi>Rage</hi> and <hi>Spight</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lay buried in the drowſy arms of <hi>Night.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It was not yet the wiſhed time, which they</l>
                     <l>Reſolv'd to make a black and bloudie day.</l>
                     <l>In fair <hi>Battalia</hi> lay theſe warlike <hi>Bands,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With wearied limbes ſtretcht on the frigid ſands:</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Muſquets</hi> neare them, readie to be found</l>
                     <l>At firſt alarm: upon the champian ground</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:16773:30"/>Their <hi>Spears</hi> moſt orderly erected ſtood,</l>
                     <l>Like to ſome ſquare and even-planted wood.</l>
                     <l>Here one his Helmet caſteth from his head,</l>
                     <l>And for a pillow underneath doth ſpread:</l>
                     <l>Another there upon a rugged ſtone</l>
                     <l>His drowſie head moſt willingly hath thrown.</l>
                     <l>Now did the dampiſh Earth their <hi>Spirits</hi> cool,</l>
                     <l>Who ſcarce of late their burning heat could rule.</l>
                     <l>Here on his back a tired <hi>Souldier</hi> lies,</l>
                     <l>And doth behold the ſtarres with ſtedfaſt eyes;</l>
                     <l>As if in them he ſearched to deſcrie</l>
                     <l>What was appointed for his <hi>Deſtinie;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ev'ry ſtarre, that twinkling doth appeare,</l>
                     <l>He thinks doth tremble with preſaging fear:</l>
                     <l>Then turns aſide, and folds acroſſe his arms,</l>
                     <l>And ſeeks to drown theſe thoughts with ſleepie charms.</l>
                     <l>Here did a <hi>Souldier</hi> with amazed heart</l>
                     <l>And troubled thoughts, like one affrighted, ſtart:</l>
                     <l>His dreaming <hi>Phanſie</hi> made him to ſuppoſe</l>
                     <l>That he was round encompaſſed with foes;</l>
                     <l>And too too plainly (as he thought) he view'd</l>
                     <l>How they in ſunder had their ſquadrons hew'd:</l>
                     <l>He ſnatcht his readie Weapon, and begun</l>
                     <l>To look how he their feared rage might ſhunne:</l>
                     <l>As round he caſts his terrour-ſtricken eyes,</l>
                     <l>Nothing but cauſe of horrour he deſcries:</l>
                     <l>He ſees his Fellows on the ground are ſpread</l>
                     <l>No otherwiſe then wounded men and dead:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:16773:30"/>He had no heart nor power to flie; but ſtayes</l>
                     <l>Till time and ſpace diminiſht his amaze.</l>
                     <l>Many brave <hi>Chieftains</hi> on the earth did lie,</l>
                     <l>Having no other Cov'ring but the Skie,</l>
                     <l>No eaſier Pillow then the rugged Ground,</l>
                     <l>No ſofter Mantle then their <hi>Arms</hi> they found:</l>
                     <l>They ſtretcht their limbes, as if they ſought what room</l>
                     <l>And ſpace would ſerve them for a future tombe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Renown'd <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> whom delicious eaſe</l>
                     <l>And Courtly ſoftneſſe never once could pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>In middle of his armed bands did reſt;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe troubled thoughts a thouſand cares moleſt:</l>
                     <l>His Royall heart with ſadneſſe almoſt ſinks,</l>
                     <l>As oft as on his weightie charge he thinks:</l>
                     <l>A World of lives now hazarded did lie</l>
                     <l>Upon the ſingle fortune of his <hi>Die.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Remembring this, his over-burd'ned Soul</l>
                     <l>Innum'rous Fears and doubtfull thoughts doth roll:</l>
                     <l>It by no humane tongue can be expreſt,</l>
                     <l>How many cares his noble heart diſtreſt,</l>
                     <l>Who for ſo many thouſands did endure</l>
                     <l>All that ſuch troubled motions could procure:</l>
                     <l>The burning agitations of his breaſt</l>
                     <l>Depriv'd his ſp'rits of their deſired reſt;</l>
                     <l>And thoſe moiſt vapours, which the brain did ſend</l>
                     <l>To cauſe refreſhing ſleep, their heat did ſpend.</l>
                     <l>So doth <hi>Sols</hi> ſcorching beams, which are reflected</l>
                     <l>Upon the land where <hi>Memphis</hi> is erected,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:16773:31"/>Where <hi>Nilus</hi> fertiliſing ſtream doth flow,</l>
                     <l>Where their high tops the <hi>Pyramids</hi> do ſhow:</l>
                     <l>Thoſe liquid vapours, which the Earth in rain</l>
                     <l>Expects to be returned down again,</l>
                     <l>Are by the <hi>Sunnes</hi> ſo pow'rfull heat made rare,</l>
                     <l>And then do vaniſh into ſubtil aire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now the ſoft-gliding <hi>Starres</hi> were ſeen t'have runne</l>
                     <l>Half round the Earth, when <hi>Swethlands</hi> Prince begun</l>
                     <l>With eyes erected to the Heav'ns, t'invoke</l>
                     <l>Th' All-pow'rfull God of warre: and thus he ſpoke;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dreadfull</hi> Jehovah, <hi>who didſt firſt inſpire</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Into my heart this vig'rous heat fire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And didſt inflame me with a</hi> Rage divine,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That I might tame theſe enemies of thine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And free thoſe</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>who with grones and cries</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Have pierc'd ſo often the all-cov'ring skies:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Be pleaſed now this</hi> Enterpriſe <hi>to bleſſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And our</hi> Deſignes <hi>to crown with good ſucceſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou know'ſt</hi> (O Lord) <hi>I neither fight for</hi> Fame,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nor yet on Earth to winne a</hi> Glorious Name:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>'Twas not the ſcope of thoſe my painfull toils,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus to enrich my ſelf with ill got</hi> Spoils:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nor do I thus with</hi> Warres <hi>theſe</hi> Lands <hi>o'rewhelm,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That I might ſtretch the limits of my</hi> Realm:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But 'twas the inſtinct of thy</hi> Pow'r above,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That to this high</hi> Deſigne <hi>my heart did move.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If any other ſiniſter intent</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Be in my heart, let not thy aid be lent:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:16773:31"/>
                        <hi>No further do we pray for</hi> Victories,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then in thy</hi> Name <hi>we onely enterpriſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The ſable <hi>Night</hi> being vaniſht, a black <hi>Day</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Begins his fatall luſtre to diſplay:</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Phebus,</hi> who foreſaw what dire miſhap</l>
                     <l>Was drawing on, his mournfull face did wrap</l>
                     <l>Within a muffled vail, a foggie miſt,</l>
                     <l>Which did the piercing of his beams reſiſt;</l>
                     <l>And thus he ſeemed to extend the night</l>
                     <l>By this obſcuring of his cheerfull light.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But notwithſtanding ſuch a ſad preſage,</l>
                     <l>Did both theſe <hi>Armies</hi> boil with longing rage</l>
                     <l>To meet each other, and to trie whoſe ſteel</l>
                     <l>Should ſooneſt make their oppoſites to reel.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Rang'd in <hi>Battalia,</hi> both the <hi>Armies</hi> ſtood,</l>
                     <l>Reſolv'd ere long to march in ſtreams of bloud.</l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>Imperiall Viceroy</hi> did preſent a fair</l>
                     <l>And ſpatious <hi>Front</hi> rankt with exacteſt care:</l>
                     <l>To ſuch a diſtance both their Wings did ſtretch,</l>
                     <l>As ſixteen furlongs full their breadth could reach.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Right Wing Coloredo</hi> did command,</l>
                     <l>Under whoſe <hi>Banner</hi> ord'red now they ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Readie prepared at their <hi>Captains</hi> Breath</l>
                     <l>Boldly to meet inevitable Death.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Friedland</hi> did his colours ſpread</l>
                     <l>In the <hi>Main Battell,</hi> which by him was led.</l>
                     <l>Count <hi>Henrick Holck Felt Marſhall</hi> for that day</l>
                     <l>In the <hi>Left Wing</hi> his <hi>Banner</hi> did diſplay.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:16773:32"/>Here divers <hi>Nations</hi> had from Countreys farre</l>
                     <l>Been ſent to trie the Fortune of the Warre.</l>
                     <l>There might you ſee the <hi>Auſtrian,</hi> whoſe <hi>Name</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is branded with an execrated <hi>Fame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For that their <hi>Princes</hi> in ambitious rage</l>
                     <l>Did with theſe warres the <hi>Germane</hi> Lands engage;</l>
                     <l>And to enrich themſelves with others ſpoil,</l>
                     <l>So many <hi>States</hi> with diſcords did embroil:</l>
                     <l>The cold <hi>Hungarian,</hi> whoſe bord'ring lands</l>
                     <l>Are ever harried with <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Bands,</l>
                     <l>Who his beſt <hi>Cities</hi> have alreadie wonne,</l>
                     <l>And half his <hi>Territories</hi> overrunne;</l>
                     <l>Though he could ſcarce be ſpar'd, yet here he came,</l>
                     <l>In this fierce fight to winne perpetuall <hi>Fame:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The bold <hi>Bohemian,</hi> whoſe fruitfull ſoil</l>
                     <l>Had been the ſtage of bloudie <hi>Mars</hi> erewhile,</l>
                     <l>Who had them taught to think moſt dang'rous fights</l>
                     <l>But warlike ſports and tragick-pleaſing ſights.</l>
                     <l>Next unto theſe was ſeen the <hi>Palatine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſpoiled Countrey borders on the <hi>Rhine;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who, as he flowing by, their ruines views,</l>
                     <l>With tears and cryſtall drops his banks bedews,</l>
                     <l>And grieves to think his waves could not o'rewhelm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>And quench the fires of that deplored Realm.</l>
                     <l>The ſtout <hi>Bavarian</hi> doth likewiſe claim</l>
                     <l>Within this catalogue a noted <hi>Name:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Him did Revenge fire with a Martiall ſpight</l>
                     <l>Gladly to trie the hazard of a Fight.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:16773:32"/>The ſunne-burnt <hi>Spaniards</hi> too were preſent there;</l>
                     <l>And if proud looks their <hi>Enemies</hi> could fear,</l>
                     <l>Sure, though but few they were, yet they alone</l>
                     <l>A greater <hi>Armie</hi> would have overthrown.</l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>Italian,</hi> now renowned more by farre</l>
                     <l>For am'rous Courtſhip, then for skill in Warre,</l>
                     <l>Yet hither came, reſolved for to die,</l>
                     <l>Or to defend <hi>Romes</hi> hated <hi>Monarchie.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And now, my <hi>Muſe,</hi> repeat each great <hi>Commander,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That did attend <hi>Swedens</hi> Imperiall Standard:</l>
                     <l>For ſure it is not fit their <hi>Names</hi> ſhould die,</l>
                     <l>Or yet in dark oblivion buried lie.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Duke Bernard,</hi> the ſole Glorie of the day,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Left Wing</hi> did for their prime <hi>Guide</hi> obey.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>King</hi> himſelf did the <hi>Right Wing</hi> command,</l>
                     <l>And at the Head of <hi>Steinbocks</hi> Troups did ſtand.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Battell</hi> was conducted by <hi>Grave Neel,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A valiant <hi>Swethe,</hi> and clad in ſhining ſteel.</l>
                     <l>Betwixt them and the <hi>Rear</hi> a compleat Band</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Muſquettiers</hi> did <hi>Hinderſon</hi> command,</l>
                     <l>A hardie and experienc'd <hi>Scot,</hi> whom <hi>Fame</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hath in theſe warres eternis'd with a Name.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Battell</hi> of the <hi>Rear Knipphauſen</hi> led,</l>
                     <l>A Noble Souldier, and a skilfull Head;</l>
                     <l>To whoſe fair conduct did their Enemies owe</l>
                     <l>The greateſt part of their ſad overthrow.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Right Wing Bulach</hi> led, a Colonell</l>
                     <l>Of no ſmall Spirit, as his foes can tell.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:16773:33"/>
                        <hi>Erneſt</hi> of <hi>Anhalt</hi> did the <hi>Left Wing</hi> guide,</l>
                     <l>A man in Warres well exercis'd and tri'd.</l>
                     <l>Behinde their backs, and in the utmoſt <hi>Rear,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A <hi>Regiment</hi> of <hi>Horſe</hi> reſerved were,</l>
                     <l>Which are by <hi>Oeme</hi> conducted, whoſe ſtout heart</l>
                     <l>Not any dangers could have made to ſtart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now had <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> ſpeech his ſouldiers fir'd,</l>
                     <l>And double vigour into them inſpir'd:</l>
                     <l>Make me (ſayes he) your Pattern; if you ſee</l>
                     <l>That once I ſhrink, I give you leave to flee.</l>
                     <l>This having ſpoken, without further pauſe,</l>
                     <l>With ſpeedie hand his ſhining blade he drawen:</l>
                     <l>Then waving't o're his head, he doth advance</l>
                     <l>Toward his Foes with fearleſſe countenance.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And now their throats thoſe fierie <hi>Engines</hi> ſtretch,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſound and furie ſuch a diſtance reach,</l>
                     <l>And ere one can behold or ſee his Foe,</l>
                     <l>Doth wound him deadly with a farre-ſent blow.</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Aetna's</hi> ſulph'rie cell inclos'd doth lie</l>
                     <l>(If we will credit grave <hi>Antiquitie</hi>)</l>
                     <l>A Monſtrous <hi>Giant,</hi> who is priſon'd there,</l>
                     <l>For that to fight 'gainſt Heav'n he did not fear:</l>
                     <l>As often as he turns his ſides for room,</l>
                     <l>He fills <hi>Trinatria</hi> with a pitchie fume,</l>
                     <l>Diſgorging from his helliſh jawes ſuch ſmoke</l>
                     <l>And duskie flames, as the pure aire do choak.</l>
                     <l>Ev'n thus black <hi>Lutzen</hi> for a time did ſhroud</l>
                     <l>Her mournfull face within a pitchie cloud,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:16773:33"/>Proceeding from the <hi>Cannons</hi> fierie breath,</l>
                     <l>That ne'r ſpeaks leſſe then ſlaughtring, wounds &amp; death.</l>
                     <l>No ſight doth now appeare, but the bright blaze</l>
                     <l>Which the inflamed ſulph'rie duſt doth raiſe.</l>
                     <l>Here many Noble Spirits, who did ſcorn</l>
                     <l>To ſhrink for dangers, were in ſunder torn</l>
                     <l>By thoſe reſiſtleſſe Balls, whoſe furious Courſe</l>
                     <l>Cannot be ſtopt by any humane force.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Oh how my <hi>Muſe</hi> deplores the <hi>Fates</hi> of thoſe,</l>
                     <l>Who nothing wiſht but to behold their foes;</l>
                     <l>That ſo their Valour, when they once had tri'd,</l>
                     <l>Might by their Enemies be teſtifi'd!</l>
                     <l>Some murd'ring ſhot their noble thoughts prevents,</l>
                     <l>And furiouſly their corps in ſunder rents;</l>
                     <l>And, which their manly hearts could not endure,</l>
                     <l>Kills them within a cloud of ſmoke obſcure.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The angrie Steeds, offended at the noiſe</l>
                     <l>That thundred from the <hi>Cannons</hi> iron jawes,</l>
                     <l>Do fling and ſpurn; and ſcarce the curbing rein</l>
                     <l>Can their proud ſp'rits in any rank contain:</l>
                     <l>They fain would ruſh through midſt of ſmoke and fire,</l>
                     <l>As if their breaſts did burn with greater Ire.</l>
                     <l>The ſlaughtred heaps that round about them lie,</l>
                     <l>Cannot at all their Courage terrifie:</l>
                     <l>The brazen Trumpet Echoes in their eares,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe pleaſing ſound doth fright away all feares.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>What <hi>Muſe</hi> is able to rehearſe or tell</l>
                     <l>What direfull ſlaughters in this fight befell;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:16773:34"/>When humane Bodies onely do oppoſe</l>
                     <l>Againſt the <hi>Cannons</hi> caſtle-rending blowes,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Furie would make hardeſt rocks to ſhiver,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe very ſound doth make the earth to quiver,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe helliſh breath is able to command</l>
                     <l>Moſt firm-cemented ſtones to fly like ſand?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Squadrons</hi> of men were too weak walls to ſtay</l>
                     <l>Such dreadfull force, as would have found a way</l>
                     <l>Through Rocks of hardeſt iron, and would make</l>
                     <l>A ſpatious Tower with its blaſt to ſhake.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No wonder then to ſee the field ſo ſpread</l>
                     <l>With ſcatt'red limbes, and bodies ſtrucken dead;</l>
                     <l>When as the <hi>Cannon</hi> and the <hi>Culvering</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Their flaming furie round about do fling.</l>
                     <l>A murd'ring <hi>Curto</hi> here a rank doth ſpoil,</l>
                     <l>And there another ſweeps away a file:</l>
                     <l>A brace of <hi>Demi-cannons</hi> here doth play,</l>
                     <l>Which through a ſquadron make a rugged way.</l>
                     <l>So bluſtring <hi>Boreas,</hi> when his rage he doubles,</l>
                     <l>And Sea and Land with furious motion troubles,</l>
                     <l>From ſturdieſt Oaks their rended branches throwes,</l>
                     <l>And all the field with theſe his ruines ſtrowes.</l>
                     <l>The unaffrighted <hi>Swethes</hi> marcht forward ſtill,</l>
                     <l>And up again thoſe breaches quickly fill.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Valiant <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> with an angrie eye</l>
                     <l>Sees how his foes their greater ſhot did ply</l>
                     <l>With too too much advantage: for he found</l>
                     <l>Their Pieces mounted on the higher ground;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:16773:34"/>And on firm platforms the <hi>Imperialiſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His <hi>Ordinance</hi> could traverſe as he liſt,</l>
                     <l>While that the <hi>Swediſh</hi> more uncertainly</l>
                     <l>Did in their motion at their Foes let flie.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Swethes</hi> had left them now no other way</l>
                     <l>To hinder this their ſo unequall play,</l>
                     <l>But on their <hi>Cannons</hi> mouthes to march, and ſo</l>
                     <l>To ſtop their throats, and make them overthrow</l>
                     <l>Their own defenders. For theſe <hi>Engines</hi> are</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a helliſh temper, that they care</l>
                     <l>Neither for friend nor foe; but both alike</l>
                     <l>With equall ſlaughter will their furie ſtrike.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In ancient fights, when as they us'd t'advance</l>
                     <l>In their firſt front a ſquare of <hi>Elephants,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who whereſoe're their unreſiſted force</l>
                     <l>They chanc'd to bend, they made an headlong courſe,</l>
                     <l>And with their maſſie Bodies over-laid</l>
                     <l>All that their furie would have checkt or ſtaid:</l>
                     <l>Sometime on their own <hi>Squadrons</hi> they would turn,</l>
                     <l>And under feet their chiefeſt friends would ſpurn</l>
                     <l>With ſuch a vengefull Rage, as if that thoſe</l>
                     <l>They had miſtaken for their deadlieſt foes.</l>
                     <l>Thus in theſe modern Warres it oft doth chance,</l>
                     <l>That the loud-roaring Shot and <hi>Ordinance</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Being once reverſt upon their friends will thunder,</l>
                     <l>And without mercie tear their ranks in ſunder.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Courage, my Hearts,</hi> cries <hi>Swethlands</hi> noble <hi>King;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And then his troups through ſhow'rs of lead doth bring</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:16773:35"/>Juſt in the <hi>Cannons</hi> face, who roar'd and ſpake</l>
                     <l>So loud, that all the neighb'ring Hills did quake.</l>
                     <l>But in their way a traverſe ditch was made,</l>
                     <l>From whence with frequent ſhot their Enemies plaid</l>
                     <l>Full in their teeth. This trench them ſafe did hide,</l>
                     <l>And made them all the <hi>Swediſh</hi> ſhot deride;</l>
                     <l>Till the provoked <hi>Swethes</hi> came ſtorming on,</l>
                     <l>And made them wiſh them further off and gone.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>At that ſame time the <hi>Crabats</hi> had a minde</l>
                     <l>To fall upon their carriages behinde,</l>
                     <l>To ſeiſe upon their Arms and Ammunition,</l>
                     <l>And to blow up their Powder and Proviſion.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bulach</hi> obſerves them with a watchfull eye;</l>
                     <l>He charg'd them home, and made them quickly flie.</l>
                     <l>Theſe light-arm'd <hi>Crabats</hi> never uſe to ſtand</l>
                     <l>For any ſpace, and fight it hand to hand;</l>
                     <l>But if at firſt encounter they have miſt,</l>
                     <l>They then reſolve no longer to reſiſt;</l>
                     <l>But turning faces do retire amain,</l>
                     <l>Waiting till <hi>Fortune</hi> ſhall be pleas'd again</l>
                     <l>Some fitter opportunitie to ſend,</l>
                     <l>And then th' are readie for to reoffend.</l>
                     <l>Thus the wilde <hi>Hawk,</hi> whom never humane art</l>
                     <l>Hath yet inſtructed with a conſtant heart,</l>
                     <l>With ſhort and ſudden flights purſues her prey,</l>
                     <l>And will not long in ſuch an action ſtay:</l>
                     <l>If that ſhe cannot winne them with a ſnatch,</l>
                     <l>For ſome more fit occaſion ſhe will watch.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:16773:35"/>But while that <hi>Bulach</hi> did return his <hi>Horſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To their firſt ſtation with a wheeling courſe,</l>
                     <l>They break their order, and had now begun</l>
                     <l>Not in fair <hi>Squadrons,</hi> but in heaps to runne.</l>
                     <l>Surely it is no eaſie thing to force</l>
                     <l>So many <hi>Regiments</hi> of head-ſtrong Horſe</l>
                     <l>To keep a full proportion in their ſpeed,</l>
                     <l>And not beyond their ord'red bounds proceed.</l>
                     <l>But then the <hi>Heav'ns,</hi> unwilling to permit</l>
                     <l>Their Foes ſhould ſpie a ſeaſon too too fit</l>
                     <l>To reaſſail them, at the inſtant ſpace</l>
                     <l>Did with a vap'rie miſt ſurround the place,</l>
                     <l>And hides them, till their confus'd cornets are</l>
                     <l>Ralli'd again, and made compleat and ſquare.</l>
                     <l>Thus <hi>Venus</hi> once her warlike <hi>Sonne</hi> did ſhroud</l>
                     <l>Within the circle of an hollow cloud;</l>
                     <l>Which armour, though but weak it was, prevents</l>
                     <l>The blowes of <hi>Fortune,</hi> and all fear'd events.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now bold <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> and th' <hi>Imperiall Horſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Had met each other with an headlong courſe.</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Regiment</hi> they were of <hi>Cuiriaſsiers,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe compleat Armour freed them from all fears.</l>
                     <l>But thou <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> in whoſe haughtie breaſt</l>
                     <l>Not any ſpark of fear could ever reſt,</l>
                     <l>Thy offred Armour didſt refuſe, and choſe</l>
                     <l>Thy Royall <hi>Bodie</hi> naked to expoſe</l>
                     <l>Againſt a ſtorm of lead, which oft doth paſſe</l>
                     <l>Through hardeſt ſteel, through iron, &amp; through braſſe.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:16773:36"/>'Tis not a valiant <hi>Heart,</hi> and <hi>Coat</hi> of <hi>Buffe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That in theſe warres is <hi>Armour</hi> proof enough.</l>
                     <l>Rare <hi>Jewels</hi> do deſerve a coſtly Caſe,</l>
                     <l>And to be lodg'd within the ſafeſt place:</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Thou,</hi> the rareſt <hi>Jewell</hi> of this Age,</l>
                     <l>O're-ſway'd I know not by what Martiall <hi>Rage,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Would'ſt not at all thy Princely limbes incloſe</l>
                     <l>In any <hi>Arms,</hi> or <hi>Steel</hi> repulſing blowes.</l>
                     <l>Was it becauſe thy too too narrow <hi>Fate</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>Caſsiopeian</hi> ſtarre did antedate,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe glorious rayes were ſeen but for a time</l>
                     <l>To be diſplaid over thy warlike clime?</l>
                     <l>Or was it, as w' have all conjectur'd ſince,</l>
                     <l>Our great unworthineſſe of ſuch a <hi>Prince,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That thus hath ſhort'ned thy victorious dayes,</l>
                     <l>Which hath all <hi>Europe</hi> ſtagg'red with amaze?</l>
                     <l>If ardent wiſhes might have proved charms,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhould'ſt have had impenetrable arms,</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch well-temp'red <hi>Steel,</hi> and of ſuch might,</l>
                     <l>As ſhould a <hi>Culvering</hi> deride and ſlight;</l>
                     <l>As ſhould have made a <hi>Cannons</hi> Maſſie Ball</l>
                     <l>Without tranſpiercing back again to fall;</l>
                     <l>Of firmer <hi>Metall,</hi> then that ſolid <hi>Plate</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Vulcans Cyclops</hi> once did fabricate</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Venus Sonne,</hi> when he the <hi>Latian</hi> ſoil</l>
                     <l>With farre-ſent warres and ſlaughters did embroil;</l>
                     <l>Of better temper, and compacted more</l>
                     <l>Then that ſame <hi>Armour</hi> which <hi>Demetrius</hi> wore,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:16773:36"/>Which the <hi>Greek Artiſt</hi> did ſo firm contrive,</l>
                     <l>That without fracture it could backward drive</l>
                     <l>A maſſie arrow from an <hi>Engine</hi> ſhot,</l>
                     <l>And never ſhrink, nor give, nor yeeld a jot.</l>
                     <l>But theſe our wiſhes of no vertue were:</l>
                     <l>They with our breath are vaniſht into aire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For ſee! Renown'd <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> murdred lies.</l>
                     <l>Here with full tears my <hi>Muſe</hi> doth cloſe her eyes,</l>
                     <l>Not willing longer to behold the light;</l>
                     <l>But fain with him would vaniſh out of ſight.</l>
                     <l>He that could never conqu'red be, is ſlain;</l>
                     <l>And He that ne're would yeeld, is pris'ner ta'ne.</l>
                     <l>He, upon whom the hopes of thouſands ſtood,</l>
                     <l>Is ſunk, and now lies weltring in his bloud.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Armies</hi> life is ſtricken with pale death:</l>
                     <l>Like-dying men they ſtruggle (ſee!) for breath.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He, from whoſe hand was ſent that curſed lead,</l>
                     <l>That with <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> ſtruck ſo many dead,</l>
                     <l>Liv'd not to triumph, no nor ſcarce to view</l>
                     <l>What he had done: a Storm of Bullets flew</l>
                     <l>Like lightning at him, and his wretched <hi>Soul</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>An hundred wayes did from his <hi>Bodie</hi> roll.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But ſoon as e're th' <hi>Imperialiſt</hi> had found</l>
                     <l>That Great <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> had his mortall wound,</l>
                     <l>With doubled Furie and Couragiouſneſſe</l>
                     <l>Th' amazed <hi>Swethes</hi> they did both charge and preaſſe,</l>
                     <l>Who now began to ſhrink and backward ſtart.</l>
                     <l>Oh! can you blame them, when th' had loſt their <hi>Heart;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:16773:37"/>Him, whom his <hi>Foes</hi> ſtill fear'd, though he were ſlain,</l>
                     <l>And thought it <hi>Valour</hi> for to wound again</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Royall Corps,</hi> whoſe very <hi>Breath</hi> and <hi>Name</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So many <hi>Armies</hi> heretofore could tame?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Juſt at this time a duskie Miſt did fall:</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Heav'ns</hi> lamented his ſad <hi>Funerall,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſo amaz'd his <hi>Foes,</hi> that they forget</l>
                     <l>To bear away his <hi>Bodie:</hi> For as yet</l>
                     <l>Among a heap of ſlaughtred Corps it lies;</l>
                     <l>A ruefull Spectacle to mortall eyes,</l>
                     <l>To ſee him laid ſo low, that was of Late</l>
                     <l>The glorious <hi>Head</hi> of ſuch a mightie State.</l>
                     <l>But by this time the <hi>Swethes</hi> had recollected</l>
                     <l>Their Sp'rits, and now again their hearts erected.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Stollhanſhe,</hi> enraged with a furious courſe,</l>
                     <l>Leads on a <hi>Regiment</hi> of nimble <hi>Horſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who gave th' <hi>Imperialiſt</hi> a charge ſo hot,</l>
                     <l>And with ſuch frequent volleys of their ſhot,</l>
                     <l>As they not able to endure, begun</l>
                     <l>To yeeld their ground, ſuch furious blowes to ſhunne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Then the ſad <hi>Swethes</hi> did raiſe a mournfull crie,</l>
                     <l>When on the ground their murdred <hi>King</hi> they eye;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe bloud-diſtained Corps in heavie ſort</l>
                     <l>From furie of the <hi>Battell</hi> they tranſport.</l>
                     <l>Meanwhile the <hi>Swediſh Foot</hi> did backward beat</l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>Imperialiſt,</hi> and made them to retreat.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Grave Neels,</hi> a valiant and couragious <hi>Swethe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That never car'd for wounds, nor fear'd for death,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:16773:37"/>His <hi>Yellow Regiment</hi> ſo bravely led,</l>
                     <l>That now they might have di'd their <hi>Name</hi> quite red.</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Winckle</hi> too with his <hi>Blew Regiment</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>At that ſame time ſo ſtoutly forward bent,</l>
                     <l>That now the <hi>Wall'nſteiners</hi> did gladly chooſe</l>
                     <l>Their ground and <hi>Cannon</hi> both at once to loſe.</l>
                     <l>But then the Miſt to ſuch a thickneſſe grew,</l>
                     <l>That the enraged <hi>Swethes</hi> could not purſue</l>
                     <l>This their advantage; but were then compell'd</l>
                     <l>To ſtand and pauſe untill the miſt diſpell'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>At that ſame time a ſudden ſtrange affright</l>
                     <l>On part of the <hi>Imperiall</hi> Troups did light,</l>
                     <l>That with ſuch terrour ſtruck their courage dead,</l>
                     <l>That ſtraight they turn'd their bridles, and then fled;</l>
                     <l>Not once their eyes reflecting back, to view</l>
                     <l>If any foes behinde them did purſue.</l>
                     <l>Some mutt'ring tongues a fearfull rumour ſpread,</l>
                     <l>That all their <hi>Troups</hi> were fully vanquiſhed.</l>
                     <l>Some fifteen hundred <hi>Horſe</hi> were then beheld</l>
                     <l>With ſwift Career to gallop out of field.</l>
                     <l>Fear taught them haſte, and made them cruell too;</l>
                     <l>For in their headlong ſpeed their friends they ſlew:</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Bedets</hi> and their <hi>Women</hi> in the Rear</l>
                     <l>They trampled down, and ſome they kill'd with fear.</l>
                     <l>There many <hi>Ladies,</hi> who that day did wait</l>
                     <l>With trembling hearts upon their <hi>Husbands</hi> Fate,</l>
                     <l>Fling from their Coaches, then their Harneſſe part;</l>
                     <l>(What will not fear enforce a tender heart?)</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:16773:38"/>In Manly poſture did theſe <hi>Females</hi> ſtride</l>
                     <l>Their ſturdie Beaſts, and ſo away they ride.</l>
                     <l>Theſe fear-tormented Wights my Warlike <hi>Muſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Doth ſcorn to follow, when none elſe purſues.</l>
                     <l>Return we to thoſe Noble <hi>Hearts,</hi> who ne're</l>
                     <l>Would ſhrink a jot, though all the world ſhould fear;</l>
                     <l>That now in midſt of fire and ſmoke did ſtrive</l>
                     <l>Their Enemies before them for to drive.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now <hi>Pappenheim</hi> being come, did reinforce</l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>Imperiall</hi> troups with new ſupplies of Horſe:</l>
                     <l>He added Courage to their ſtagg'ring <hi>Bands,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And made them charge again with willing Hands.</l>
                     <l>He rang'd himſelf in the <hi>Siniſter Wing,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which (as he thought) oppoſed <hi>Swethlands King.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But as his <hi>Cornets</hi> now ſtood ord'red fair,</l>
                     <l>And he himſelf did for the Charge prepare,</l>
                     <l>A Bullet from a <hi>Falconet</hi> is ſent,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe deadly force his arm and ſhoulder rent:</l>
                     <l>Soon it tranſcoloured his ſhining Steel</l>
                     <l>With bloud, and made this haughtie <hi>Captain</hi> reel;</l>
                     <l>He that the town of <hi>Magdenburg</hi> did ſpoil,</l>
                     <l>And levell'd all her buildings with the ſoil;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe <hi>Execrations,</hi> as we may preſume,</l>
                     <l>Did haſten on his unexpected Doom.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But when his <hi>Captains</hi> and <hi>Commanders</hi> ſaw</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Generall</hi> his lateſt breath to draw,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He's ſlain, He's ſlain,</hi> aloud they all did crie;</l>
                     <l>Then facing it about, away they flie,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:16773:38"/>Ere they had fought one ſtroke, or in the field</l>
                     <l>The faces of their <hi>Enemies</hi> beheld.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But thoſe <hi>Imperials,</hi> whom his preſence ſet</l>
                     <l>On a freſh charge, ſtood to it ſtiffly yet,</l>
                     <l>And with ſuch maſſie <hi>Squadrons</hi> overlaid</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Swediſh</hi> Troups, that they were backward ſwaid.</l>
                     <l>Here <hi>Coloredo,</hi> and <hi>Terſica</hi> too,</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Picolomini,</hi> the fight renew</l>
                     <l>With no ſmall Furie, and with many hands</l>
                     <l>Which light upon <hi>Grave Neels</hi> and <hi>Winckles</hi> Bands.</l>
                     <l>The firſt of theſe above the knee being hurt,</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Souldiers</hi> from the <hi>Battell</hi> did tranſport,</l>
                     <l>Though after this he did not long ſurvive.</l>
                     <l>And thou brave <hi>Winckle</hi> wert fetcht off alive</l>
                     <l>With double wounds. But thy <hi>Vice-Colonell</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Was ſtricken down, and did not ſcape ſo well.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though thus th' <hi>Imperialiſt</hi> victoriouſly</l>
                     <l>Did for a while the <hi>Swediſh Squadrons</hi> plie,</l>
                     <l>And now his <hi>Cannon</hi> had reſum'd again,</l>
                     <l>Which erſt he loſt; yet for it was he fain</l>
                     <l>T' exchange ſo many of his braveſt men,</l>
                     <l>The flow'r of all his <hi>Infantrie,</hi> and then</l>
                     <l>So ſoon their deer-bought bargain to give over,</l>
                     <l>Which the bold <hi>Swethes</hi> quickly from them recover.</l>
                     <l>There did old <hi>Bruner</hi> on th' <hi>Imperiall</hi> part,</l>
                     <l>A skilfull <hi>Captain,</hi> loſe both life and heart.</l>
                     <l>The young Count <hi>Wall'nſtein</hi> by ſome unknown hand</l>
                     <l>Was likewiſe there ſhot dead upon the ſand.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:16773:39"/>There <hi>Fulda's Abbot</hi> di'd, whoſe ſacred head</l>
                     <l>Was pierced by the rude and impious lead,</l>
                     <l>That never to diſtinguiſh yet would learn,</l>
                     <l>Nor be conjur'd a <hi>Mitre</hi> to diſcern</l>
                     <l>From a ſteel <hi>Helmet,</hi> but impartially</l>
                     <l>At all alike his unſtaid force doth flie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Here had the fierceſt of the <hi>Battell</hi> been,</l>
                     <l>Here likewiſe was the greateſt ſlaughter ſeen.</l>
                     <l>The ſturdie <hi>Swethes</hi> had learn'd to fight and die;</l>
                     <l>But never yet had learn'd to ſhrink or flie:</l>
                     <l>The ground, which erſt their warlike hands defended,</l>
                     <l>They cover with their <hi>Bodies</hi> now extended.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Death</hi> well might winne from them their lives; but loe,</l>
                     <l>Their ground he cannot force them to forgo.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But now <hi>Knipphauſen,</hi> who with watchfull eye</l>
                     <l>The ſlaughter of his <hi>Vantguard</hi> did deſcrie,</l>
                     <l>Moſt readie is to ſtop encroaching fear:</l>
                     <l>He ſends them up two <hi>Brigades</hi> from the Rear:</l>
                     <l>The one Count <hi>Thurn,</hi> the other <hi>Mitzlaffe</hi> led,</l>
                     <l>Who gladly did their waving Colours ſpread,</l>
                     <l>And marching forward with a ſpeedie pace,</l>
                     <l>Their now triumphing <hi>Enemies</hi> do face.</l>
                     <l>Having within a reaching diſtance got,</l>
                     <l>They did ſalute them with their thundring ſhot,</l>
                     <l>Which without ceaſing they ſo roundly pli'd,</l>
                     <l>That now th' <hi>Imperials</hi> hearts were terrifi'd:</l>
                     <l>Being ſo lately tired, they could not</l>
                     <l>For any ſpace endure a <hi>Charge</hi> ſo hot.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:16773:39"/>What could be done by Valour or by Skill,</l>
                     <l>Was there perform'd; they ſtand it out, untill</l>
                     <l>The eager <hi>Swethes</hi> by force and weightineſſe</l>
                     <l>Expell'd them from the place they did poſſeſſe.</l>
                     <l>Once more th' <hi>Imperiall Cannon</hi> they had wonne;</l>
                     <l>And turning them, to thunder now begun</l>
                     <l>Againſt the <hi>Wall'nſteiners.</hi> At that ſame houre,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bernard,</hi> that noble <hi>Duke,</hi> with all his Power</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Foot</hi> fiercely aſſails thoſe bands</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Regiments,</hi> where <hi>Coloredo</hi> ſtands;</l>
                     <l>Who did as then, like ſome unmoved rock,</l>
                     <l>Receive th' impreſſion of his mightie ſhock:</l>
                     <l>At which the <hi>Duke</hi> did ſlacken his firſt heat,</l>
                     <l>And back again did orderly retreat.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But here once more the vap'rie miſt deſcended,</l>
                     <l>And for a while both ſides from blowes defended.</l>
                     <l>But when this cloudie curtain drawn aſide</l>
                     <l>Gave ſpace to both the <hi>Armies</hi> to be ey'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wall'nſtein</hi> did two of his chief <hi>Captains</hi> ſend</l>
                     <l>To ſee what now the <hi>Swethlanders</hi> intend.</l>
                     <l>At that time <hi>Bernard</hi> and <hi>Knipphauſen</hi> joyn'd,</l>
                     <l>And both together had their <hi>Troups</hi> combin'd:</l>
                     <l>Their ſhatt'red <hi>Regiments</hi> they did repair</l>
                     <l>With freſh ſupplies, and made them ſtraight &amp; ſquare.</l>
                     <l>Theſe <hi>Scouts</hi> return'd, and to their <hi>Duke</hi> relate</l>
                     <l>How that the <hi>Swediſh</hi> meant to iterate</l>
                     <l>The fight afreſh and did in Battell ray</l>
                     <l>Their bloudie Enſignes once again diſplay,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:16773:40"/>And orderly were marching on amain,</l>
                     <l>Reſolving for to conquer or be ſlain.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Duke <hi>Bernard</hi> doth eſpie th' <hi>Imperiall Horſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Retreating from them in an even courſe;</l>
                     <l>Then twentie <hi>Cannons</hi> did he make to roar</l>
                     <l>With ſuch a vengefull furie, that they tore</l>
                     <l>Both Horſe and Man, defac'd both rank and file,</l>
                     <l>And their fair Martiall order quickly ſpoil,</l>
                     <l>Making their troups confuſedly to ſhow,</l>
                     <l>While on the graſſe their mingled bloud doth flow;</l>
                     <l>And which before not any colour knew,</l>
                     <l>But the freſh green, is di'd with purple hue.</l>
                     <l>Here the proud <hi>Steed,</hi> who ſcorn'd &amp; ſpurn'd the ground,</l>
                     <l>Stretcht dead upon the ſame is quiet found:</l>
                     <l>And there another, who did fiercely neigh,</l>
                     <l>And bravely did his reared creſt diſplay,</l>
                     <l>Is with a fire-wing'd bullet ſtricken dead,</l>
                     <l>And mangled lies without a creſt or head:</l>
                     <l>Here was a file of <hi>Horſemen</hi> cut in ſunder</l>
                     <l>By direfull force of this reſiſtleſſe thunder,</l>
                     <l>While th' untoucht <hi>Horſe</hi> do ſtart and fling about,</l>
                     <l>And ſo the next diſorderly do rout.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Swediſh Cornets</hi> ſoon th' advantage ſpie,</l>
                     <l>And with a ſudden charge upon them flie.</l>
                     <l>Before it thundred; now a ſtorm of hail</l>
                     <l>And ſmaller ſhot their ſtagg'ring troups doth quail;</l>
                     <l>And then theſe haughtie <hi>Cavaliers</hi> begun</l>
                     <l>With ſwift and more diſord'red pace to runne.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:16773:40"/>Their <hi>Infantrie</hi> no better then did fare;</l>
                     <l>Theſe alſo by the <hi>Swethes</hi> repulſed are,</l>
                     <l>Who now preſt on, and pli'd their <hi>Volleys</hi> round,</l>
                     <l>And ſhouldred out th' <hi>Imperials</hi> from their ground.</l>
                     <l>As when two <hi>Currents</hi> do adverſely roll,</l>
                     <l>And ſeek each others motion to controll:</l>
                     <l>A while they ſeem pois'd with an equall force,</l>
                     <l>And both alike repell their ſpatt'ring ſourſe;</l>
                     <l>Till one of them aſſiſted with a blaſt,</l>
                     <l>The others waves doth headlong backward caſt:</l>
                     <l>Thus did the <hi>Swethes</hi> by force and Martiall toil</l>
                     <l>Compell th' <hi>Imperials</hi> backward to recoil.</l>
                     <l>But thoſe that in the mud-wall'd Gardens lay,</l>
                     <l>Farre more ſecurely for a while did play,</l>
                     <l>Under protection of thoſe earthen Banks,</l>
                     <l>Upon the <hi>Swethlanders</hi> encroaching ranks.</l>
                     <l>But they, enrag'd at this unequall fight,</l>
                     <l>Advanced tow'rds them with a vengefull ſpight;</l>
                     <l>And like a Tempeſt ſtorm'd upon their trenches,</l>
                     <l>Which ſoon with ſlaught'red bloud their furie drenches.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And now the <hi>Sunne,</hi> wearied with this ſad ſight,</l>
                     <l>Began from them to hide his ſhining light:</l>
                     <l>He now did ſeem with his declining beams</l>
                     <l>To kiſſe the <hi>Oceans</hi> azure-colour'd ſtreams;</l>
                     <l>When lo a rumour was diſperſt by ſome,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Pappenheims Foot-Regiments</hi> were come:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Duke Bernard</hi> then rallies again his Horſe,</l>
                     <l>Reſolv'd t'aſſail them with his utmoſt force.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:16773:41"/>But when the <hi>Signall</hi> was again reſounded,</l>
                     <l>The cheerfull <hi>Souldiers,</hi> as no whit aſtounded,</l>
                     <l>Strictly did each embrace his <hi>Camerade,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, <hi>Muſt we charge them once again?</hi> they ſaid;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then let us bravely and with manly Hearts,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And like true</hi> Souldiers, <hi>act our lateſt parts.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then with ſuch rage and furie did they cloſe,</l>
                     <l>As if they had reſerved all their blowes</l>
                     <l>For this laſt onſet; and thoſe new-come Bands</l>
                     <l>Did quickly feel their over-weightie hands:</l>
                     <l>They found that though the light did ſtill decreaſe,</l>
                     <l>Yet the ſtout <hi>Swethes</hi> would not their furie ceaſe.</l>
                     <l>After they had ſuſtained for a while</l>
                     <l>Their rough encounter, and no little ſpoil,</l>
                     <l>They did betake them to a ſhamefull flight</l>
                     <l>Under protection of the wings of Night,</l>
                     <l>Leaving the field to their victorious foes,</l>
                     <l>Who on the ſame their wearied limbes repoſe.</l>
                     <l>Among his wounded Friends and Enemies,</l>
                     <l>On the cold ground the conqu'ring <hi>Souldier</hi> lies;</l>
                     <l>And ne're complaineth of ſo hard a Bed,</l>
                     <l>Where VICTORIE her pleaſing arms hath ſpread.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:41"/>
                  <p>AN ELEGIE UPON THE IM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MATURE AND MUCH LAMENTED DEATH OF that moſt Chriſtian Souldier and Renowned Prince, GVSTAVVS THE GREAT, King of Swethes, Goths, and Vandals; &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Compoſed immediately after the firſt rumour of his death, by JOHN RUSSELL.</p>
                  <p>¶ Printed by the Printers to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie</hi> of CAMBRIDGE. 1634.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:42"/>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:16773:42"/>
                  <head>An Elegie upon the death of the King of <hi>SWEDEN.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat ſtrange ſad ſilence doth the world aſtound?</l>
                     <l>Why doth not <hi>Fames</hi> ſtill echoing trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſound?</l>
                     <l>She's grown forgetfull, or elſe hoarſe, I fear,</l>
                     <l>That we no more victorious ſounds can heare.</l>
                     <l>'Twas but of late, when as the thundring noiſe</l>
                     <l>Of doubled triumphs, conqueſts, and applauſe</l>
                     <l>Fill'd our <hi>Horizon,</hi> and the aire did ring</l>
                     <l>With ſhouts of praiſse to <hi>Sweds</hi> victorious King.</l>
                     <l>Was this a dream and fanci'd apparition,</l>
                     <l>And now is vaniſht like a fleeting viſion?</l>
                     <l>Could all the world be thus deluded? No:</l>
                     <l>'Twas ſurely reall, and no feigned ſhow.</l>
                     <l>Thoſe bloudie battels and thoſe diſmall fights</l>
                     <l>We lately heard, were not like vap'rie ſights,</l>
                     <l>Compos'd of airie breath, which to the eye</l>
                     <l>Two dreadfull <hi>Armies</hi> grappling do deſcrie.</l>
                     <l>Theſe, theſe were reall; and thy direfull ſteel</l>
                     <l>(Victorious Prince) ſhall after-ages feel:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:16773:43"/>And thoſe deep wounds, which in thy furious ire</l>
                     <l>Thou didſt inflict by force of thundring fire,</l>
                     <l>Shall leave wide ſcarres upon the <hi>Germane</hi> land,</l>
                     <l>Which ſhall for ever to their terrour ſtand.</l>
                     <l>This thou haſt done alreadie, and amaz'd</l>
                     <l>Remoteſt kingdomes, where thy deeds are blaz'd.</l>
                     <l>But on a ſudden, loe! thou doſt appeare</l>
                     <l>To ſtop in middle of thy full career:</l>
                     <l>All tongues are ſilent, and our greedie eares</l>
                     <l>Heare nothing now but terrours, doubts, and fears.</l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Fame</hi> her ſelf is dead; or he that gave</l>
                     <l>Life unto <hi>Fame,</hi> is ſunk into his grave.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fame</hi> cannot die. Oh! can he die, whoſe look</l>
                     <l>So many thouſands dead at once hath ſtrook?</l>
                     <l>What mortall durſt give him a wound, whoſe eye</l>
                     <l>Hath made grimme <hi>Death</hi> to ſtart and turn awrie?</l>
                     <l>Sure he's not dead: <hi>Swethland</hi> for grief would roar,</l>
                     <l>And make their grones heard to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhore,</l>
                     <l>If he were dead, whom they have priz'd more deare</l>
                     <l>Then their own proper lives, and did not fear</l>
                     <l>To runne like <hi>Lions,</hi> at their Princes words,</l>
                     <l>Upon the mouthes of <hi>Cannons,</hi> points of Swords.</l>
                     <l>He's dead, I fear: For can he living be,</l>
                     <l>And we no ſpoils nor further conqueſts ſee?</l>
                     <l>Can he be living, and not heard to thunder,</l>
                     <l>To batter cities, trample kingdomes under;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe very ſoul was fire Aethereall pure,</l>
                     <l>Such as no mortall bodies can endure?</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:16773:43"/>His breath was direfull ſmoke, and from his hands</l>
                     <l>Flew ſhow'rs of iron balls, that quell'd whole lands.</l>
                     <l>Can that <hi>Sulphurious</hi> duſt, more quick then winde,</l>
                     <l>Once toucht with flame, in priſon be combin'd?</l>
                     <l>Not ſteel, nor iron, nor the hardeſt braſſe</l>
                     <l>Can ſtay its furie for the ſhorteſt ſpace.</l>
                     <l>Though mightie mountains preſt this living flame,</l>
                     <l>Yet would it tear them, and an entrance frame,</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Helliſh</hi> breath and diſmall noiſe to vent;</l>
                     <l>Nor would it ceaſe, till all its furie's ſpent.</l>
                     <l>Thus hath it been with <hi>Europes</hi> Northern Starre,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Sweds</hi> Victorious <hi>Prince,</hi> made all for warre:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe <hi>Spirit,</hi> toucht with fire from heav'n, did blaze</l>
                     <l>Like to ſome <hi>Comet,</hi> ſent for to amaze</l>
                     <l>And ſcourge us mortall wights; whoſe direfull breath</l>
                     <l>Doth ſhoot down vengeance, terrours, plagues, &amp; death.</l>
                     <l>Had <hi>Turk,</hi> and <hi>Tartar,</hi> and the <hi>Triple Crown</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That awes the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world, and treadeth down</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Monarchs</hi> as ſlaves, themſelves in one combin'd;</l>
                     <l>This <hi>Heav'n-ſent Furie</hi> had, like lightning winde,</l>
                     <l>Shot through them all; and, like to ſcatt'red corn,</l>
                     <l>Their feeble ſquadrons had been rent and torn:</l>
                     <l>Till his <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> vigour were quite ſpent,</l>
                     <l>No <hi>Warres,</hi> no <hi>Ruines</hi> could his ire content.</l>
                     <l>But now his date is out, and his <hi>Commiſsion</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is ſtopt from heav'n with a new <hi>Prohibition.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He's dead.</hi> Oh bitter word, enough to make</l>
                     <l>Stones for to weep, and iron hearts to ake!</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:16773:44"/>So ſoon? alas! in ſo unwiſht an houre</l>
                     <l>Is all our joy quell'd by ſome ſecret power?</l>
                     <l>Why do not we then breathe ſuch dolefull grones,</l>
                     <l>And poure ſuch melting tears, as ſhould hard ſtones</l>
                     <l>Diſſolve into ſalt drops; that they and we</l>
                     <l>Might ſo expreſſe one mournfull <hi>Elegie?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What! are we ſpent and drie? I ſee no teares;</l>
                     <l>I heare no grones; no wailings pierce my eares.</l>
                     <l>Oh pardon me! I fear my faltring tongue,</l>
                     <l>Diſtract with troubled ſorrow, doth you wrong.</l>
                     <l>'Tis ſlender grief that doth by weeping vent;</l>
                     <l>And 'tis not much that can by tears be ſpent.</l>
                     <l>But this, this ſorrow, like a mortall wound,</l>
                     <l>Strikes deep, and doth our ſenſes quite aſtound;</l>
                     <l>Lies like a lump of lead or heavie weight</l>
                     <l>Upon our heart, and pincheth it ſo ſtrait,</l>
                     <l>That neither ſigh nor grone can iſſue thence;</l>
                     <l>But lies as dead, and quite bereft of ſenſe.</l>
                     <l>Since then 'tis ſo we cannot weep; let's borrow</l>
                     <l>From others help, ſo to expreſſe our ſorrow.</l>
                     <l>Ye gliſtring lamps above, ye Northern ſtarres,</l>
                     <l>That roll about the <hi>Pole</hi> your frozen Carres;</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Thetis</hi> waves plunge over head and eares,</l>
                     <l>That ye may have your fill of briniſh teares,</l>
                     <l>And by ſad influence make the heav'ns to lowre,</l>
                     <l>And to the earth ſend down a weeping ſhowre;</l>
                     <l>But chiefly on that place, that curſed ground,</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Adolph</hi> firſt receiv'd his mortall wound.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:16773:44"/>Let never graſſe nor verdant herb grow there;</l>
                     <l>Nor any tree, nor ground it ſelf appeare.</l>
                     <l>Let it be all a lake, whoſe face may look</l>
                     <l>Juſt like the colour of th' Infernall brook;</l>
                     <l>Like pitchie <hi>Styx,</hi> or black-ſtream'd <hi>Acheron;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or like <hi>Cocytus,</hi> or dark <hi>Phlegethon:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That it may ſeem to all a mourning vail,</l>
                     <l>That doth the ſurface of that ground empale.</l>
                     <l>And let its murm'ring waves make ſuch a noiſe,</l>
                     <l>As may expreſſe to us the dolefull voice</l>
                     <l>Of ſome that crie, that roar, that ſhriek, that grone;</l>
                     <l>Of ſome that mourn, that weep, that wail, that mone:</l>
                     <l>That after-ages to their children may</l>
                     <l>Tell this ſad ſtorie, when they paſſe that way;</l>
                     <l>Theſe ſouls do mourn for <hi>Swethlands</hi> conqu'ring King:</l>
                     <l>But theſe, whoſe clamours fearfully do ring,</l>
                     <l>Are ſuch as in this place di'd by his power,</l>
                     <l>And thus expreſſe their horrour to this houre.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Meanwhile, Renowned <hi>Prince,</hi> ſleep thou ſecure,</l>
                     <l>No further pains nor travels to endure.</l>
                     <l>The dreadfull Cannons, which ſo oft did roar</l>
                     <l>And thunder in thy eares, ſhall now no more</l>
                     <l>Diſturb thy reſt, nor force thee to ariſe</l>
                     <l>In ſudden haſte: glut now with ſleep thine eyes,</l>
                     <l>While that a Quire of <hi>Angels</hi> in a ring</l>
                     <l>Shall round about thee bleſſed muſick ſing.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16773:45"/>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:16773:45"/>
                  <head>EPICEDIVM, SIVE Carmen Funebre, GVSTAVI ADOLPHI, Suecorum, Gothorum, &amp; Vandalorum, &amp;c. Regis Invictiſſimi <hi>MEMORIAE SACRVM.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Uiſquis es, &amp; tumuli ſpectas haec Marmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra nigri,</l>
                  <l>Quae cernas, oculis perlege flebilibus.</l>
                  <l>Ille, cui vivo libârunt ſanguinis undas,</l>
                  <l>Defunctus lacrymas vendicat (ecce!) tuas.</l>
                  <l>Nónne vides, madidis ut ſplendent Marmora guttis?</l>
                  <l>Sudorem lapidum forſitan eſſe putas:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:16773:46"/>Sive repercuſſos quos frigida ſaxa vapores</l>
                  <l>Duritie nimià congenuêre ſuâ.</l>
                  <l>Ah! non ſunt. Sacris, Spectator, credito <hi>Muſis:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sunt lacrymae, atque oculis debita rapta piis.</l>
                  <l>Nè numerum ſtupeas: tota hîc <hi>Europa</hi> dolores</l>
                  <l>(Ut cernas) madidos egemuêre ſuos.</l>
                  <l>Et, niſi quòd Pietas vetet hoc, mactare parâſſent</l>
                  <l>Ad tumulum vitas millia multa ſuas.</l>
                  <l>Nil minùs in campo tecum, <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAVE,</hi> libenter</l>
                  <l>Magna Caterva (vides) occubuiſſe velint:</l>
                  <l>Et, quò deſcendas ad <hi>Regna Inferna</hi> triumphans,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Victoríſque</hi> inſtar clara Trophaea feras;</l>
                  <l>Captivorum <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrae</hi> moeſtè tua Signa ſequuntur:</l>
                  <l>Implentur diris <hi>Tartara</hi> nigra ſonis.</l>
                  <l>Invidiâ &amp; lacrymis iterum ſibi vulnera figunt;</l>
                  <l>Et miſerè ſubeunt bis ſua <hi>Fata</hi> necis.</l>
                  <l>Sed tu magnanimâ cinctus, <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAVE,</hi> cohorte,</l>
                  <l>Fauſtis &amp; niveis pergito vectus equis;</l>
                  <l>Donec in <hi>Elyſii</hi> campis ſpatieris amoeni:</l>
                  <l>Illìc <hi>Heroum</hi> turba beata manent.</l>
                  <l>Secula felices ducunt ſine fine futura,</l>
                  <l>Aeterníſque ardent pectora laetitiis:</l>
                  <l>Et feriunt aures mortalibus uſquè negati</l>
                  <l>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us, Siderei quos ſonuêre Poli.</l>
                  <l>Haec mihi divino retulit ſpiramine <hi>Phoebus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Et juſſit numeris reddere nota meis;</l>
                  <l>Nè <hi>Suecus,</hi> vel qui <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STAVI</hi> funera deflent,</l>
                  <l>Immerſi lacrymis in ſua <hi>Fata</hi> ruant.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:16773:46"/>Qui viſus fuerat violento <hi>Numine</hi> raptus,</l>
                  <l>Et quaſi devictus ſuccubuiſſe neci,</l>
                  <l>In nova migravit felicia Regna; Triumphat,</l>
                  <l>Oſtentans Stygiis magna trophaea diis:</l>
                  <l>Inter &amp; <hi>Heroas,</hi> &amp; coetum <hi>Semideorum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Jam ducat laetos &amp; ſine fine Choros.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. R.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="dialogue">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:16773:47"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>DIALOGVS.</hi> Vmbra GVSTAVI ADOLPHI, &amp; Fama.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Umb.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ò ducis? Quò <hi>Fama</hi> juvat volitare? receſſus</l>
                     <l>Quos petis ignotos? Patrias jam liquimus oras.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fam.</speaker>
                     <l>Me duce carpe viam: ſedes tibi <hi>Fama</hi> beatas</l>
                     <l>Oſtendet. Petimus <hi>diviſos orbe Britannos.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Non unus <hi>Suecûm GUSTAVO</hi> ſufficit orbis.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Umb.</speaker>
                     <l>Siſte fugam; ſatìs eſt nobis: de Marmore ſurgit</l>
                     <l>In Patria Tumulus; celſo ſtruxêre Columnas</l>
                     <l>Vertice ſubnixas, Monumentáque ſplendida fulgent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fam.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Quae Monumenta ſonas? memoras quae Marmora?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>GUSTAVI Manes</hi> anguſto pixide condi.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fama</hi> &amp; <hi>Fata</hi> vetant: longè meliora parantur Sordent</l>
                        <l>Oſsibus (en!) Monumenta tuis: non fictilis urna</l>
                        <l>Te capit; at <hi>Muſis</hi> deſcripta volumina ſacris</l>
                        <l>Nomina <hi>GUSTAVI</hi> aeterno ſplendore fovebunt.</l>
                        <l>Optatas jamjam <hi>Muſarum</hi> attingimus oras.</l>
                        <l>Cernis, ut irriguis ſtagnare paludibus undae</l>
                        <l>Contendunt, geminóque procul Mons vertice ſurgit?</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="79" facs="tcp:16773:47"/>
                           <hi>Pieridum</hi> ille cluit <hi>Parnaſſus.</hi> Limpidus amnis,</l>
                        <l>Deliciae <hi>Phoebi,</hi> doctis hîc labitur undis.</l>
                        <l>Hîc <hi>Vatem, GUSTAVE,</hi> tuum ſpectato ſonorum,</l>
                        <l>Cui mentes animúmque afflârunt Numina ſancta.</l>
                        <l>Cernis, ut incedit ſudans ſtipante catervâ</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pieridum?</hi> Flammis (en!) luxuriantur ocelli:</l>
                        <l>Oratument. Furit haud aliter <hi>Cumaea Sibylla,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Fatidicos quoties ignes inſpiret <hi>Apollo.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Ecce locum ſparſum foliis, ubi <hi>Fata</hi> recondit</l>
                        <l>Inclyta <hi>GUSTAVI,</hi> mediíſque inſculpat ovantem</l>
                        <l>Te ſpoliis. Juvat has latè diſpergere Chartas,</l>
                        <l>Nomina <hi>GUSTAVI</hi> reſonent ut murmure rauco</l>
                        <l>Et Sylvae, &amp; Venti: reſponſans accinet <hi>Echo.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Jam patrias ſedes repetáſque cubilia terrae:</l>
                        <l>Et dum Terra Parens cupidis circundabit ulnis</l>
                        <l>Oſſa, gemens ſecum tua <hi>Fata</hi> ſuprema volutet;</l>
                        <l>Inſuetóſque halitus, tanquam ſuſpiria, mittat,</l>
                        <l>Percutiénſque ſinum tremulo eructabit hiatu.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. S. Magd. <hi>Coll.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
